<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true principles of the Christian education of children briefly and plainly declared and recommended to parents and all others concerned in the institution of youth. Very profitable for all sorts of persons, as containing the great and fundamental truths and duties of the Christian religion. / Translated from the second edition of the original French.</title>
            <author>Poiret, Pierre, 1646-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2743A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181913</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299211</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04766)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2808:55)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true principles of the Christian education of children briefly and plainly declared and recommended to parents and all others concerned in the institution of youth. Very profitable for all sorts of persons, as containing the great and fundamental truths and duties of the Christian religion. / Translated from the second edition of the original French.</title>
                  <author>Poiret, Pierre, 1646-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 93 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Reid,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year, M. DC. XCV. [1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [31].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian education of children --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of House</figDesc>
                  <q>1915</q>
                  <head>LAURISTON · CASTLE</head>
                  <q>William Robert Reid</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:2"/>
            <p>THE True Principles OF THE CHRISTIAN EDUCATION OF CHILDREN Briefly and Plainly Declared and Recommended to PARENTS and all Others Concerned in the Inſtitution of YOUTH <hi>Very profitable for all Sorts of Perſons, as containing the Great and Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Truths and Duties of the CHRISTIAN RELIGION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated from the ſecond Edition of the Original <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>For I know him <hi>(Abraham)</hi> that he will Command his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and his Houſehold after him, and they ſhall keep the Way of the <hi>LORD,</hi> to do Juſtice and Judgement, that the <hi>LORD</hi> may bring upon <hi>Abraham</hi> that which he hath ſpoken of him, <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen: 18.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Reid,</hi> in the Year, M.DC.XCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:3"/>
            <p>Remember now thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the dayes of thy Youth, while the evil dayes come not, nor the years draw nigh, when thou ſhalt ſay, I have no pleaſure in them, <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 12.1.</bibl>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:3"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>THAT the Education of Children is of vaſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Conſequence, will (I doubt not) be readily acknowledged by all; The truth is, the Injunctions given to Parents on this ſcore, in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture are ſo frequent, and ſo ſolemn, and the Advantages of a good Education, are ſo many and ſo Valuable, that no thinking Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons can be inſenſible of the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:179950:4"/>
of it. But in the mean time it is ſad to obſerve that this great Concern is as univerſally, either wholly neglected, or but ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and trifflingly mannaged, as the Importance of it ſeems to be univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally acknowledged. Some Parents indulge themſelves in a wretched and unnatural careleſneſs, as to the Education of their Children; Some are ignorant of the true Meaſures of accompliſhing it; And others do adopt and ſteer their courſe by either falſe or imperfect Maxims.</p>
            <p>It is certain that Chriſtians ought to madnage the Education of their Children, according to the Preſcripts of the Chriſtian Religion: This is the Bleſſed Magazin or Storehouſe, out of which they muſt take Tools and Materials, for rendring their Souls agreeable to GOD, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them for the Glories of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. This is the Doctrine, to uſe the
<pb facs="tcp:179950:4"/>
Apoſtles Phraſe, <hi>Into which they muſt be delivered:</hi> This is the Mould on which they muſt be Formed: And hence muſt the Salt be fetched, that ought to ſeaſon theſe tender Hearts. Young Ones muſt be timeouſly taught, <hi>To determine to know nothing but JESUS CHRIST, and Him Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.2.</note> The Example of His Holy Life, His Croſs, His Sufferings, and Death, and conformity to Him in theſe, and all other things, are very ſeriouſly to be recommended to them. They muſt be train'd up in the Love of ſelf-denyal, contempt of the World, and reſignation to the will of GOD. The Excellencie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfulneſs, and and neceſſity of theſe practices, are to be carefully repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to them: They muſt be early acquainted with <hi>the ſtraite &amp; narrow way,</hi> the way of the Croſs, of Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and of Mortification, as a way that's Lovely, pleaſant, and full of
<pb facs="tcp:179950:5"/>
peace and comfort, and <hi>leading unto Life Eternal.</hi> They are further to be made ſenſible of the great Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of human nature, &amp; of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Spirit, and Grace of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in order to Enlighten, purifie, &amp; heal the dark, unclean, and diſeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Souls of Men: The Spirit, courſes and practiſes of the wicked World; as alſo the Motions &amp; Inclinations, the Luſts and Paſſions of depraved nature muſt be defamed, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraged to them: For theſe prompt to the purſute of Carnal Eaſe and pleaſure, of ſelf-ſatisfaction and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of Riches and Plenty, of Honour and Greatneſs; Which deſires are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable to a ſtate of tryal, ſuch as is our condition in this World, and in which we are oblidged to perſevering and patient labour, and watching, fighting, and wreſtling, running, &amp; ſtriving. In a word, to educate <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> Chriſtianly, is, to <hi>Diſciple them
<pb facs="tcp:179950:5"/>
to the Holy JESUS,</hi> and to oblidge them to trace the foot-ſteps of their dear Redeemer, to conform to ſo Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine a Patern in every thing; to learn of him to be Meek &amp; lowly in heart, &amp; <hi>to take his eaſy &amp; pleaſant Yoke upon them, and ſo they ſhall find reſt to their Souls.</hi> Theſe are great and Noble things, and ſuch as are very proper to be inſtiled into young Hearts, as ſoon as poſſible, that ſo from their Infancie, they may learn to <hi>know CHRIST, and the power of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the fellowſhip of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, being made conformable to his Death.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Phil: 3.10.</note> Theſe are things, that Books which pretend to give an account of the <hi>Meaſures of a Chriſhian Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> ſhould eſpecially point at, and direct unto: And I cannot but look on it as an eſſential defect in Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this nature, when ſuch matters as theſe are either not at all touched, or but little and ſlightly inſiſted on in them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179950:6"/>The little tract that follows, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accidentally, or rather by a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py providence fallen into my hands I was after a ſerious and deliberate peruſal, ſoon convinced; That it did not fall ſhort of its Title, that is, that in my opinion it ſolidly, &amp; judiciouſly layes down the great &amp; foundamental Principles of a Pious, and Chriſtian Education; And this conviction prompted me, for the common Good of Mankind, to attempt a Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, being aſſured, that in doing this, I would do a conſiderable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and kindneſs to all ſerious and well diſpoſed hearts. I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to put the Tranſlation in as plain and ſimple a dreſs of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and to keep as near the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal, as poſſibly I could, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any additions, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that for the benefit of the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er I have preſented him on the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, With a brief and ſummary view
<pb facs="tcp:179950:6"/>
of the Contents of each Section.</p>
            <p>I perſwade my ſelf, that all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Parents, and Inſtructers of Youth, all that are tender of their own, and their Childrens Spiritual concerns, and Eternal Salvation, will look on it as a very Fortunate rencountre, that a Book is put in their hands which furniſhes them with Excellent Advices, for mannaging this Great Truſt, and that in a way that is Eaſie, Familiar and Compendious, and ſuited to the Capacities of all that are of Honeſt, Candid, and Serious Diſpoſitions: It is true, none are here to expect to be taught the Rules of Civility; Or to be inſtructed in the method of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Languages, and Humane Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, No, this was not in the Authors View; Neither could he deſign it, it being indeed wholly Forraign to the Concerns of a <hi>Chriſtian Education.</hi> All that is pretended to be done in
<pb facs="tcp:179950:7"/>
this Performance, is to affoord the beſt Directions, for Faſhioning and Dreſſing the Souls of Young Ones, in order to partake in the Glories of Eternity, This is the Butt, and Mark, at which a Chriſtian Education ſhould eſpecially Level, and all the directions that are offered, ſhould be ſuited and accomodated to this great end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the meaſures here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed have viſibly this Character, being indeed the great eſſentials, the Marrow and Subſtance of the Goſpel, which are here recommended; firſt, to the ſerious conſideration, and practice of the Parents; that ſo by means of their Holy examples, and diligent inſtructions, and by the Bleſſing of GOD upon their Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Endeavours, theſe great Truths may be ſavingly imparted to, and inculcated on their Children.</p>
            <p>The Pious Author having been importuned by a Great and Worthy
<pb facs="tcp:179950:7"/>
Friend of his, to give directions how to mannage aright the Education of Children, though for ſome time he declined to comply to this requeſt; Yet in end, he was prevailed with to impart his Thoughts, but ſtill without any deſign of making them publick, till at laſt it was concluded, that it would greatly ſerve the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of all Conſcientious Inſtructers of Youth to have ſuch an excellent Help put in their hands. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor addreſſed theſe Directions to his Friend, in the Form, and confin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to the Bounds of a Letter, whereby he was obliged not to draw out his Thoughts to any great length, and ſo gives but the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or firſt principles of a Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Education; However the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples which he hath laid down, as they are True and Genuine, ſo they are Fertile and Comprehenſive, and capable to ſuggeſt to all attentive
<pb facs="tcp:179950:8"/>
and penetrating Minds, whatever is neceſſary to be known on this head: But ſince few will be at the pains to make ſuch Improvements of them; and becauſe ſome do ſtand in need of more dilated and ample Accounts: Therefore the Reader may e're long, by the Divine Bleſſing and Aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, expect a full and Copious Syſtem of Directions, on the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of a Chriſtian Education; Which, however, are but Deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from, and Enlargements on, the Principles here laid down; In this larger Account, the faults and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages committed in the Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Youth are declared, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Directions are given how to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage this great Concern in all the inſtances of it to the beſt Advantage, Powerful Motives are adduced to perſwade Parents and all others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Religious Education
<pb facs="tcp:179950:8"/>
of Youth, to put what is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to them on this head in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: And in fine, a great many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, neceſſary, and yet little ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Truths, are through the whole inſiſted on.</p>
            <p>Mean while, Chriſtian Reader, Converſe with theſe Principles, read and digeſt them; They deſerve ſome of thy moſt recollected Thoughts, and thou ſhalt never, I hope, have cauſe to repent of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a few of thy moments in turning over the following pages, and that thy Reading may profit and edifie thee; I ſhall begg pardon before I cloſe, to entreat a few things of thee; One is, That thou Read with cloſs Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not content thy ſelf with a ſuperficial glance: Next, that thou do not reject, what thou doſt not at firſt underſtand, but vouchſafe it a review: And in fine, and eſpecially, that thy Peruſal be attended with a
<pb facs="tcp:179950:9"/>
ſerious Diſpoſition, for otherwiſe, all will be to little purpoſe; nay I muſt plainly tell thee, that if thou art not reſolved to <hi>deny thy ſelf, to take up the Croſs, and follow Chriſt,</hi> ſome things here will choak thee; For corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will fly in the Face of what grates hard upon it, and pinches it; And the old Man cannot endure to be roughly treated. But on the other hand, if thou deſignes to be a votary of the Spirit &amp; Croſs of the Holy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, if thou art one that worſhips God in Spirit, and places Religion, not in <hi>outward Formes</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> but in <hi>Righteouſneſs, Peace</hi> and <hi>Purity,</hi> in Life, and Power; Then what is here offered to thee, will prove ſavory and reliſhing, and the more the Truths here preſented to thee, will choak and contradict thy corrupt ſelf; Still the more agreeable they will be; And thou wilt find ſuch ſolid pleaſure and Tranquillity in the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them thy ſelf, that thou will
<pb facs="tcp:179950:9"/>
be prompted to propagate and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to all others, on whom thou canſt hope to have any influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>And, O may the Good GOD <hi>turn the Hearts of the Fathers unto the Children, and the Hearts of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their Fathers, and the Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Wiſdom of the Juſt,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mal: 4.6. Luke. 1.17.</note> And Second with his effectual Bleſſing and Grace, whatever is ſincerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to ſerve the Intereſt of Souls,</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:10"/>
            <head>THE Authors Advertiſement TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>FAthers and Mothers, and all you to whom the Education of Children is intruſted, if you underſtood well the Importance of that Charge, you would eaſily, diſcern, that all your other Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, your Imployments, your Buſineſses, your Concerns, your Goods, and your Care to get them, and to keep them, are but nothings, or but meer triffles in compariſon of it. The leaſt of theſe Souls, whereof you are oblidged to take care, is of ſuch a Value, that the Son of GOD hath eſteemed it more than his
<pb facs="tcp:179950:10"/>
own Life. Your work is to educate them for Heaven or for hell, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly if you educate them well, you ſhall together with them, as a Recompence of your Labours, enjoy a happy Eternity, or endleſs miſeries, if you neglect them, even though otherwiſe you may have liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unblameably as to your own Perſons, without mentioning any thing of the curſes of this Life, which fall on ſuch as do not fairly acquite themſelves of this duty. The holy Scripture lets us ſee, that the high Prieſt <hi>Eli,</hi> though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a Good Man, yet not having ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually enough reſiſted, and curbed the wicked inclinations of his Sons, was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for it with Death, both he and his Children, the whole people routed, the Ark taken; and all his prieſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily exterminated. It is to be feared, that the Callamities which overwhelm Chriſtendome owe their Original alſo to this: For Men do not take care to edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Children by any other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,
<pb facs="tcp:179950:11"/>
but that by which they have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten them, I mean, by the impulſe of a purely carnal Concupiſcence, whereas they ought to be acted in the whole, from a <hi>Principle of Divine Love,</hi> which prompts and influences us, to deſire that there may be yet other Creatures with us, which might joyn and unite with us, in Eternally Loving and Honouring the Majeſty of GOD. But alace, this is it of which Men take but very little thought, and there are but few who ſeriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to form Creatures, who profeſſing and living agreeably unto the great Name of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in this World, ſhould be worthy of GOD and his Eternity here after.</p>
            <p>Since the following Letter Aims only at this deſign, it was believed, that to render it publick, would be a beneficial Performance, and greatly tend to the Advantage of whoſoever will incline to make the deſigned Uſe and Improvement of it, whether with reſpect to Children, or alſo with reſpect to themſelves, how
<pb facs="tcp:179950:11"/>
aged ſoever they may be; Becauſe in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Truths that are contained in it, are of ſo comprehenſive and extended an Uſe, that at the bottom, they do no leſs agree to the adult and aged, for all their Life throughout, than to Children for their firſt years. And ſince, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Words of JESUS CHRIST, <hi>We muſt become little Children in order to inherit the Kingdom of GOD;</hi> Since the <hi>Perfection</hi> which the Goſpel requires of us is ſo great, that it will be hard to find any, for as advanced as he may think himſelf to be, who hath not juſt ground to conſider himſelf ſtill as a Child; Since the <hi>Wiſdom of GOD,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and ſaving <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine</hi> is ſo ſimple, that it is propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to the Capacity of the meaneſt, even of <hi>Children themſelves,</hi> and in fine, Since GOD doth very often in Holy Scripture, vouchſafe theſe whom he will, ſave the deſignation of <hi>Children,</hi> and of <hi>his Children,</hi> I do not believe that any ought to think himſelf harſhly treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb facs="tcp:179950:12"/>
when one ſhall tell him as I do, that when Principles are laid down for the Chriſtian Education of Children, he may well believe that excepting only a few things, which do not regard but ſome Circumſtances of Age, the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars inſiſted on do no leſs ſuit and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to him in ſubſtance, how advanced ſoever in years he may otherwiſe be then they do to thoſe who are yet but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to live: Would to GOD that Men would be perſwaded to make a Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of this, by a ſerious and continual practice of the following Truths. And as I heartily wiſh that all Parents had been themſelves oducated from their Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy according to theſe Meaſures, ſo I ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire, that, to repair what might have been amiſs as to this, they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the practice of them in their own perſons, and betimes oblidge their Young Ones to obſerve them, whiles their Souls continue flexible and complying.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>FAREWELL</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:12"/>
            <head>The Contents. Giving the READER a Summary View of the Whole.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE moſt Effectual method of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying the following Inſtructions into Young Ones, briefly laid down. <hi>SECT. 1. Page. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The chief miſtake in the Education of Children condeſcended on. <hi>SECT. 2. ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A neceſſary qualification of the Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Young Ones, namely they muſt in ſome meaſure know GOD and themſelves. <hi>SECT. 3. Page. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What they ought to know of GOD. <hi>SECT. 4. Page. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The knowledge they are to have of themſelves. <hi>SECT. 6. Page. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The principal Faculties of the Soul. <hi>SECT. 7. Page. 8.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>I. The Faculty of Deſire.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The neceſſity of improving the Faculty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Deſire in Children betimes. <hi>SECT. 8 Page. 10.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The uſe and importance of the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Deſiring, brieflie declared by a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar compariſon. <hi>SECT. 9. Page. 11.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:179950:13"/>GOD and his VVill the True and the only Object of the Deſire. <hi>SECT. 10. Page. 12</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="chapter_section">
                  <head>Conſequences from this.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I.</hi> To deny our own will and deſires. <hi>SECT. 11 Ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II</hi> To entertain low and mean thoughts of our ſelves, never deſiring the praiſes and commendations of men. <hi>SECT. 12. Page. 14.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III.</hi> To be content with the leaſt and worſt of things. <hi>SECT. 13 Page. 15</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How to kindle pious and devout incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations towards GOD in the hearts of Young Ones. <hi>SECT. 14: Page. 17.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I.</hi> From the Conſideration of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections. <hi>SECT. 15. Ibid:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II.</hi> From the conſideration of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of GOD, both paſt and preſent. <hi>SECT. 16. Page. 18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III.</hi> From the expectation of future Bleſſings, eſpecially of Spiritual Ones. <hi>SECT. 17. Page. 19</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>That our deſires may be ſucceſsful, great care muſt be taken to do the will of GOD. <hi>SECT. 18. Page. 20.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IV.</hi> From the conſideration of paſt ſins. <hi>SECT. 19. Page. 21</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The nature and indiſpenſible ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of prayer. <hi>SECT. 20 Ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What praying in the Name of CHRIST imports. <hi>SECT. 21 Ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To beget in Young Ones an habit of lifting up their Hearts to GOD, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and ſincerely, is of vaſt impor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:179950:13"/>
to their pious Education. <hi>SECT. 22 Page. 23</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Young ones muſt be taught vocal Prayers, a Caution about theſe. <hi>SECT. 23 Page. 25</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A needfull Caution about the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations that are in the Pſalms. <hi>Ibid: Page. 26</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The obligations of Parents, during the Infancie of their Children declared. <hi>SECT. 24 Page 27</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The ſad conſequences of not beginning the Education of Young Ones from the improvement of their deſire <hi>SECT. 25. Page. 28.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>II. The Faculty of Underſtanding.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Truth the object of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding. <hi>SECT. 26. Page. 29.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="chapter_section">
                  <head>Conſequences of this.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> A lie depraves the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and muſt not be endured in Children. <hi>SECT. 28 Page. 30.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Not to ſtuff our minds with the knowledge of uſeleſs things. <hi>SECT. 29. ibid:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How the Faculty of knowing is exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in man. <hi>SECT. 30. Page. 31.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> The <hi>Underſtanding</hi> ſince the fall is blind as to Divine Things. <hi>SECT. 31. ibid:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>We muſt believe what we do not yet Divinely ſee. <hi>SECT. 32. Page. 32.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Principle and Light of Faith. <hi>SECT. 33 Page. 33.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Young Ones are to be guarded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the abuſe and deluſions of corrupted <hi>Reaſon. SECT. 34 Page. 34.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How this may be beſt done, is declared by a Compariſon. <hi>SECT. 35. ibid:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:179950:14"/>Of what nature the diſcoveries are, that corrupted Reaſon makes of Divine Things. <hi>SECT. 36. Page. 35.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The great Principle which with reſpect to human Reaſon muſt be betimes engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in all hearts. <hi>SECT. 37. Page. 36</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What to do in order to be divinely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned. <hi>SECT. 38. Page. 37.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The right method of exerciſing the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Young Ones. <hi>SECT. 39. Page. 38.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The happy Advantages of this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. <hi>SECT. 40. Page. 40.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>That the imagination of Young Ones muſt be early improven. <hi>SECT. 41. Page. 41.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A neceſsary caution with reſpect to it. <hi>SECT. 42. Page. 42.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter_section">
                  <head>Three wayes of exerciſing it.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> By Reading. <hi>SECT. 43. Page. 43.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> By acquainting them with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance and meaning of the Belief. <hi>SECT. 44. ibid:</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter_section">
                  <head>Where three things are to be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to their notice.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1. GOD</hi>'s Gracious Deſigns and Conduct with reſpect to man, both in his Creation and Redemption. <hi>SECT. 45. Page. 44.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> The Converſation of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST in our Humanity as deſigned for our imitation. <hi>SECT. 46. Page. 45.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> That the Father, Son, and Holy
<pb facs="tcp:179950:14"/>
Ghoſt mentioned in the Belief are but One <hi>GOD. SECT. 47. Page. 46.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What it is to know the Holy Trinity in a Divine and Saving manner. <hi>SECT. 48. Page. 48.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Another way of improving the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination and memory of Young Ones: <hi>SECT. 49. Page. 50</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>III. The Faculty of Rejoiceing.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>An Account of this faculty, the ground of it very early miſtaken, <hi>SECT. 50: Page. 51.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>GOD only the ground of Rejoicing, <hi>SECT. 51: ibid</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="chapter_section">
                  <head>Certain grounds of Rejoicing to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate on Young Ones</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>The firſt ground, is GOD, his Divine Excellencies and Benefits. <hi>SECT. 52. Page. 53.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II.</hi> When any thing is piouſly done, whither by themſelves or by others. <hi>SECT. 53. Page. 54</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III.</hi> When they ſuffer and are reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſgraced. <hi>Ibid: Page. 56</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The uſe of the faculty of rejoicing, with reſpect to the particular, immediatly preceeding, illuſtrated by a compariſon. <hi>SECT. 54 Page. 57</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter_section">
                  <head>Innocent Divertiſement muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed young ones but with ſome Cautions</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I.</hi> That they be taught ever to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God to be the Author of
<pb facs="tcp:179950:15"/>
whatever they receive, and to thank him for it. <hi>SECT. 56 Page. 58</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II.</hi> That no objects which may grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their corrupt inclinations, be made the ground of their joy. <hi>SECT. 57 Page. 59</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III.</hi> Particularly the love of money is to be ſuppreſsed in them. <hi>SECT. 58 Page. 60</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Faculty of Rejoicing given to the Soul, that it might be fixed on God. <hi>SECT. 59 Page. 61</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Abuſe of our Joy, with reſpect to Divine things to be prevented, and how! <hi>SECT. 60 Page. 62</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>IV. The Executive Faculty.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The Divine faculties of the Soul, being well ordered, action eaſily and naturally follows. <hi>SECT. 61 Page. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The general Rule of action laid down, recommended and illuſtrated. <hi>SECT. 62 Ibid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Commands muſt he taught Young Ones firſt in the Literal, and then in the more Sublime and Spiritual import of them. <hi>SECT. 63 Page. 71</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Though what the Law Commands be impoſſible to corrupt Nature; Yet the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Jeſus makes it eaſy. <hi>SECT. 64 Page. 74</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Portions of Scripture particularized, which contain the Goſpel Law. <hi>SECT. 65 Page. 75</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An abridgement or ſhort ſumm of the Divine Laws. <hi>SECT. 66 Page 76</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:179950:15"/>Children muſt be put in mind of the Baptiſmal Covenant. <hi>SECT. 67 Page. 78</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="chapter_section">
                  <head>What Young Ones muſt practiſe.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I.</hi> With reſpect to God. <hi>SECT. 69 Page. 79</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II.</hi> With reſpect to Parents and Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors. <hi>SECT. 70 Page. 80</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III.</hi> With reſpect to their Neighbours <hi>SECT. 71 Ib:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IV.</hi> With reſpect to themſelves. <hi>SECT. 72 Page. 81</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How to mannage the reproofs and chaſtiſements of Children. <hi>SECT. 73 Page. 82</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>They muſt be taught to praiſe God when they do well. <hi>SECT. 74 Page. 84</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Parents ought conſcientiouſly to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe themſelves what they recommend to their Children. <hi>SECT. 75 Page. 85</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The fancied impoſſibility or ridiculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the foregoing directions refuted. <hi>SECT. 76 Page. 86</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The great miſery of negligent Parents <hi>Ib: Page. 87</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The happineſs of ſuch as ſhall train up their Children according to the maxims of Chriſtianity. <hi>SECT. 77 Page. 88</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="passages_of_scripture">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:16"/>
            <head>Some Paſſages of Scripture, declaring the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligations that ly on Parents, carefully to endeavour the Religious Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Childrcn.</head>
            <p>ANd ye Fathers, provoke not your Children to wrath: But bring them up in the Nurture and Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the Lord, <hi>Eph: 6.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go: And when he is old, he ſhall not depart from it, <hi>Prov: 22.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that ſpareth his Rod hateth his ſon: But he that loveth him chaſteneth him betimes, <hi>Pro: 13.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chaſten thy ſon while there is hope, and let not thy Soul ſpare for his crying, <hi>Prov: 19.18</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fooliſhneſs is bound in the heart of a child, but the rod of correction ſhall drive it far from him, <hi>Prov: 22.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Withhold not correction from the child: For if thou beateſt him with the rod, he ſhall not die, <hi>Prov: 23.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rod and reproof give Wiſdom: But a child left to himſelf, bringeth his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>other to ſhame, <hi>Prov: 29.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Correct thy Son and he ſhall give the reſt: Yea he ſhall give delight unto thy Soul, <hi>Ibid: 17. verſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="passages_of_scripture">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:16"/>
            <head>The Obligations of Children to liſten to the Inſtructions of their parents, likewayes repreſented from ſome few paſſages of Scripture.</head>
            <p>CHildren Obey your parents in the Lord, for this is right, <hi>Eph: 6.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My ſon hear the Inſtruction of thy Father, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake not the Law of thy Mother, for they ſhall be an Ornament of Grace unto thy head, and chains about thy neck. <hi>Prov: 1.8, 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hear O my ſon and receive my ſayings: And the Years of thy life ſhall be many. I have taught thee in the way of Wiſdom: I have led thee in the right paths. When thou goeſt, thy ſteeps ſhall not he ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and when thou runeſt, thou ſhall not ſtumble. Take faſt hold of Inſtruction, let her not go, keep her, for ſhe is thy life. <hi>Prov: 4. 10, 11, 12, 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hearken unto thy Father that begat thee, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not thy Mother when ſhe is old. Buy the Truth and ſell it not, alſo Wiſdom and Inſtruction and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. The Father of the Righteous ſhall great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoyce, and he that begetteth a Wiſe child, ſhall have Joy of him. Thy Father and thy Mother ſhall be glad, and ſhe that bare thee ſhall rejoice. My Son give me thine heart, and let thine Eyes obſerve my wayes. <hi>Prov: 23.22, 23, 24, 25, 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Son keep thy Fathers Commandment, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake not the Law of thy Mother. Bind them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb facs="tcp:179950:17"/>
upon thine heart, and tie them about thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> When thou goeſt, it ſhall lead thee; When thou ſlee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt, it ſhall keep thee; And when thou awakeſt, it ſhe talk with thee. For the Commandment is a lam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the Law is light; And reproofs of Inſtruction a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the way of Life, <hi>Prov: 6.20, 21, 22, 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore hearken unto me, O ye Childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For bleſſed are they that keep my wayes. Hear I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction, and be wiſe, and refuſe it not. Bleſſed the Man that heareth me: Watching dayly at my gate waiting at the poſts of my doors. For whoſo finde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Me, findeth Life, and ſhall obtain Favour of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord. But he that ſinneth againſt Me, wrongeth hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own Soul: All they that hate Me, love death, <hi>Prov. 8.32, 33, 34, 35, 36.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come ye Children, heaken unto Me: I will tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you the fear of the Lord, <hi>Pſal: 34.11.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Reader is intreated to correct the following miſtakes.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Page.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Line</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Miſtakes</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Ammendments</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>as to the mind</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>As to the mind</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Willingly</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Willing</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>on the Margent, <hi>allow them</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>allow</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Whatſoever</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Whoſoever</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>all other</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>all the other</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>caſe</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>cauſe</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>on the Margent,</hi> § 82.</cell>
                     <cell>§ 81.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>and what</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>and of what</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>if the</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>if this</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>their own</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>its own</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>deſire</cell>
                     <cell>deſires</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>deprived</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>depraved</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>§ 14. 3.</cell>
                     <cell>§ 14.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>and heart</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>an heart</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>end of end</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>end</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>as turning</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>in turning</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>to unpuniſhed</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>to paſs unpuniſhed</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>we able</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>we be able</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſee</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>ſee;</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>them</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>them,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>principal</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>principle</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>a young</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>young</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>their cauſes</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>the cauſes</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>or it is</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>for it is</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid:</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>injuried</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>injured</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſomething</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>ſomethings</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>accuſtoming</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>accuſtoming them</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>this</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>thus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>67</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>on the Margent, are</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>being</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>70</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>for the glory</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>to the glpry</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>walketh</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>walk</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>76</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſay</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>I ſay</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>77</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>unto</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>into</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>unto</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>into</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid:</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pſalms</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Pſalm</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:18"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Part,</hi> 1. <hi>Eſſay,</hi> 2. which the Reader will ſee in the running Title of ſome of the Coppies, was inſert by a miſtake.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That what is Printed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſuch Paratheſes as theſe [ ] contains the additions made to the ſecond Edition.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179950:18"/>
            <head>The JUST MEASURES Of the Pious Inſtitution of YOUTH.</head>
            <head type="sub">Containing the True Principles of a CHRISTIAN Education.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU have ſo often importuned me to write ſomething, which might be a Directory to Men in the Chriſtian E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of Children, that I cannot any longer forbear, declaring to you in a few words, that which in my opinion ought to be obſerved on this head, by all ſuch as intend to bring them up Chriſtianly.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179950:19"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>§. 1.</hi> The moſt effectual Method of conveying the following Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions into Young Ones, briefly laid down, <hi>Viz.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and other Governours muſt know, digeſt and practiſe theſe things themſelves in order to impart them ſavingly to their Children.</note>§. 1. And that I may the more happily accompliſh this deſign, I ſhall imitate theſe, who, that they may with more precaution and warineſs give Phyſick and cure to ſuch as are yet on the Breaſts, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe that the Nurſe do take it firſt, to the end, that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incorporated it in her ſelf, ſhe may afterwards commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicat it to the Sucklings in a Nutritive manner, ſeaſonably and in what meaſure ſhe ſhall judge convenient.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ſect;. 2.</hi> The chief miſtake in the Education of Children condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended on, namely too great regard had to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the Mind, without taking care of the heart and Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note>§. 2.—I am of Opinion that the Capital and Chief Errour which is committed in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of Children is, that Men greatly endeavour to improve their <hi>Mind,</hi> without taking care of their <hi>heart,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perhaps in furniſhing it with ſome Rules of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs and Civilities, with reſpect to the conduct of the World As to the <hi>Mind,</hi> which they would have awakened
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179950:19"/>
and ſtirred up in them before the <hi>heart,</hi> they content themſelves with giving it ſome Knowledges and notices after a manner, which, as it is ordinarly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, makes Children much more like <hi>Parrats,</hi> than intelligent Creatures, they only load their memory with a quantity of Queſtions and Anſwers, which it is ſufficient that they rehearſe word for word, without comprehending any thing of them, after which they are commended for this Recital, as if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they had ſufficiently diſcharged themſelves of that which they owe unto GOD: And thus it is that we learn from our Infancy, <hi>to draw near unto GOD with our Lips, while the Heart and the Soul is far from Him,</hi> As GOD complains of his people by his Prophet. <hi>Iſa:</hi> 29.</p>
            <p n="3">§. 3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>§. 3.</hi> A neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary qualification of the Inſtructers of Young Ones, they muſt in ſome meaſure know God and themſelves.</note> It were to be wiſhed, that ſuch as have Children to be educated, had ſome fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Knowledge both of GOD and of themſelves, and eſpecially of their <hi>Souls,</hi> and of what concerns them, to the end they may know from thence that which is principally to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179950:20"/>
on Children; and to be cultiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and improven in them.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">§. 4 What they ought to know of GOD.</note>§. 4. Now in my Opinion here are preſented to them ſome Inſtances of thoſe principal Notices, which it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for them to have.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Concerning <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THey ought to conſider GOD as an <hi>Eternal</hi> Beeing, or Spirit without Beginning and without end, <hi>Incompre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>henſible and Inviſible Good</hi> and the Cauſe of all Good, <hi>Powerfull</hi> to do whatſoeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> He pleaſes; <hi>Wiſe</hi> knowing and doing e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>very thing well, <hi>Happy</hi> and full of Divine Joyes, a Lover of all that which He hath made, and eſpecially of Men; moſt willingl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make theſe Eternally hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>py and Joyfull who do His Will, and leaving the reſt (the Diſobedient and In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corrigible) miſerable and deſtitute of all Good: <hi>Juſt,</hi> to render to every man according to His Works, <hi>True</hi> in His Promiſes and in his Threatnings, and <hi>Merciful</hi> in pardoning the evil to ſuch who ceaſe to do evil, and ſeek from Him the pardon of it with Love and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of heart.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:179950:20"/>§. 5.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>§. 5.</hi> Paſsages of Scripture are to be taught and explain'd to Young Ones with reſpect to the Divine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes &amp; as their Capacities will allow.</note> It would be proper to make a Child learn ſome paſſages of Scripture, with reſpect to each of theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and to let him ſee the Application of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Capacitie.</p>
               <p>For inſtance, with reſpect to that which ſayes, that GOD is an <hi>Inviſible</hi> and <hi>Incomprehenſible Spirit.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, chap: 1. verſe 18. <hi>No man hath ſeen</hi> (or comprehended) <hi>GOD at any time, the Only Begotten Son, which is in the Boſom of the FATHER, He hath declared Him.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe is that of JESUS CHRIST. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11 verſe 27. <hi>No man knoweth the SON but the FATHER, neither knoweth any Man the FATHER ſave the SON, and He to whom the SON will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal him.</hi> Whereupon, Endeavours muſt be uſed to inculcate on them from thence betimes, that all our Readings, all theſe things which we hear at Church or elſe where, all our Studies, our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations and our reaſonings, are not capable to derive unto us by themſelves, the leaſt ſpark of the True and Living
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179950:21"/>
Knowledge of GOD and of his Secrets, but that it is GOD alone who can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat it, in putting his Good Spirit, and Divine Grace, and Light into the heart of ſuch as ſhall unceſſantly pray unto Him for them, with a deep Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and an entire Reſignation and ſhall endeavour to do His Will, as far as He hath made it known to them.</p>
               <p>With reſpect to the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of GOD, JESUS CHRIST hath ſaid, <hi>There is none Good but GOD alone,</hi> From this you are to inculcate on them, that all Good comes from GOD only, both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in Earth, within Man and without Man, and that He only ought to have the Glory of it, that all which we do without him, without his Grace and Aſſiſtance is evil, and that who ſoever doth not poſſeſs GOD hath no Good, but is infinitely miſerable.</p>
               <p>With reſpect to the <hi>Power</hi> of GOD, <hi>I know whom I have believed, and am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him againſt that day,</hi> ſaith <hi>St. Paul;</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1.12. Oblige them to think on this head, that ſince we are all corrupted &amp; wholly undone by ſin, none can reſtore us to our firſt &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179950:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſtate but the Almighty GOD, and that if we confide in him, and reſign our Soul, our Life, and our Conduct un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Him, to the end that he may do with them what ſhall pleaſe Him, He can keep us by his Pow'r againſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall oppoſe our Felicity; He can deliver us from all danger, and re-eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſh at the laſt day in an eſtate of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, of Salvation and Glory, our Bodys, our Souls; and that which we have recommended to his Direction and Conduct.</p>
               <p>This ſame may be done with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to all other Attributes of GOD, which have been touched; I leave it to the care of theſe who educate Children to make the like improvements of them by ſome paſſages of Scripture, and by ſome little reflections of the ſame nature with theſe.]</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. 11. As to our <hi>Souls,</hi> there follow here ſome of the moſt important notions that reſpect them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6. 11.</hi> The knowledge of themſelves. The view that men are to have of the Soul.</note> and ſuch as are moſt accommodate to our deſign. We have a <hi>Soul</hi> which is immortal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, the which GOD hath
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179950:22"/>
Created with deſign to inhabite and take up his reſidence in it, and ſo by himſelf, who is the ſource of all good, to make it good, able to do well, wiſe, Virtuous, Juſt, True, full of Love and Charity, Happy and Joyous; Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being Adorned with ſuch Divine quali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties as theſe, he might Eternally, and Holily delight, and entertain himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with it. It is for this that we were Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>7.</hi> The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Faculties or Capacities of the Soul.</note>§. 7. It is alſo for this that GOD hath given to our <hi>Soul</hi> three or four Principal Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, or Faculties and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; Over which we muſt very carefully watch, that we may becommingly improve and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage them: For on this depends the Eternal well-fare and miſery of <hi>Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. The firſt of theſe Capacities is, <hi>the Power of Deſiring</hi> or <hi>Willing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. The Second is <hi>that of Knowing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. The third is, <hi>that of Rejoycing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. And the fourth is, <hi>that of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting and puting in practice outwardly, that which ſeems good to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:179950:22"/>[Theſe Faculties or Properties are ſo inter-woven with our <hi>Soul,</hi> and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable from it, that one may juſtly look on them as conſtituting its nature. And therefore we need not ſcruple to determine, that the <hi>Soul</hi> is a <hi>being that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to know the true good, and to injoy it, to the end that it may regulate thereby its life, and its practice to the Glory of GOD, and its own eternal wellfare</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When a <hi>Soul deſires</hi> the true good, and when it <hi>knows</hi> it, <hi>Enjoyes it,</hi> and puts it in practice, it is <hi>happy;</hi> Or at leſt it is in the <hi>aſſured way of Salvation</hi> and Happyneſs. <hi>If ye know theſe things,</hi> ſaith JESUS CHRIST, <hi>Happy are ye if ye do them. John</hi> 13.17.</p>
               <p>But when a <hi>Soul</hi> is without all deſires after the true good, without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, and without the Enjoyment and practice of it; It is Infinitely unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and in the way to Eternal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee that all depends on the good or evil conduct of theſe four Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties. Our great buſineſs in this World, is to mannage them well. Let us think ſeriouſly on this; for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it are Eternal.]</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:179950:23"/>Since we are corrupted by ſin, and ſince GOD alone is the cauſe of all good, we muſt ſeriouſly endeavour that he come and take Poſſeſſion of our <hi>Soule,</hi> and <hi>there</hi> he may Aſſiſt and Govern our <hi>Deſire,</hi> our <hi>Mind,</hi> our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> our <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and our <hi>Practice,</hi> otherwayes without him we ſhall never do any thing to purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">8. 2. The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of <hi>Deſire</hi> in Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</note>§. 8. 1. The gate by which GOD comes unto us with his moſt Holy grace, is the <hi>deſire</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> which we other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe call the <hi>Heart</hi> or the <hi>Will;</hi> and this is it which we muſt excite, cheriſh and improve in Children betimes, and that without intermiſſion. When this part ſhall go well, all the reſt will eaſily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it of their own accord; But as long as a <hi>Soul</hi> capable to uſe this facultie is without a good will, and a good Heart, that is to ſay, as long as it hath not in it ſincere and ſerious deſires after GOD, it is really without life before him, and ſhall never live with him, if it ſhall come to depart this life in that ſtate. Without this Divine deſire, all ſorts of knowledge and practices, and even the greateſt advantages of nature, of birth, and of Education ſhall ſerve for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179950:23"/>
purpoſe but to make it ſo much the more like the Devil, and as wicked, acurſed and unhappy before GOD, as he is.</p>
               <p n="9">[§. 9. The uſe of the <hi>deſire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">9. The uſe and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ifly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon.</note> and its importance with reſpect to the Soul, may be very pertinently made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to a Child, by a compariſon ſuited to his capacitie; Namely by telling him, that the <hi>deſire</hi> is to the Soul what the mouth and ſtomach are to the body. It is by the mouth and by the ſtomach that the Body receives its food, which when good doth nouriſh it; but if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome and poiſonous, indſpoſes and kills it; Juſt ſo it is by the deſire that the <hi>Soul</hi> is either Nouriſhed, or indiſpoſed and killed Spiritually, according to the nature of the things, after which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is carried. As then we muſt take good heed that we put not into the mouth, or let down into the ſtomach but whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome things; So we muſt take very great care that we do not receive into our deſire, but good things, if we would happily live the life of the <hi>Soul.</hi> For this life ſhall of neceſſity be of ſuch a conſtitution and temper as are our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and the objects which which we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179950:24"/>
admit unto them. And ſo it is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of each one to conſider ſeriouſly how he Nouriſhes his <hi>Soul,</hi> or leaves it lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, and what nature the things are to which he gives acceſs unto his deſires.]</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>10.</hi> GOD and his Will the true and the only object of the Deſire. The conſequences of this.</note>§. 10. The power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring hath been made for that which is <hi>Good,</hi> that is to ſay, for GOD, who is the only good, and for his <hi>Will,</hi> which only is the ſourſe of all good.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is that we ought not to deſire any thing but GOD, and that which is agreeable to His Holy <hi>deſire,</hi> and to his Divine will, and we muſt diſingadge and turn away our deſire from every other thing, for every other thing but GOD and his will is evil. And conſequently,</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>11. 1.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence: to deny our own will and deſires, to do which Young Ones muſt be airely in.</note>§. 11. 1. None ought to <hi>deſire his own will, nor cheriſh his own deſires, which are all evil, corrupted and the ſourſe of all ſin;</hi> On the other hand, the ſole deſire and ſole will of GOD is the <hi>ſourſe</hi> of all good.</p>
               <p>This is it to which Young
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179950:24"/>
Ones muſt be habituated as ſoon as is poſſible with the greateſt care, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and croſſing their deſire in every thing, before they have contracted the fatal habit of following their own will; But men muſt act here with diſcretion, though they muſt never fail moſt vigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to oppoſe and check this unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py impreſſion, when once it hath taken root. O how eaſie would the practice of Virtue become, if this wicked habit did make no reſiſtance to it! And if while the Spirit is moſt flexible, I mean, if from their Infancie upwards, men were formed to this great point, the which is ſo neceſſary, that no Soul ſhall ever be ſaved without having renounced their own deſires. The paſſages of the Goſpel are expreſs as to this particular: And they ought to be rendered familiar to Children, and ſo ought that Prayer of JESUS CHRIST, <hi>My Father,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 22.42.</note> 
                  <hi>not my will but Thine be done;</hi> And that other proteſtation of his, <hi>I am not come into the World to do mine own will, but the will of my Father.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">John 6.38.</note>
               </p>
               <p>[When this unhappy byaſs, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of following our own deſires, and our own will, is already become
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179950:25"/>
habitual, as it is in thoſe that are adult, we muſt not give over reſolving to make aſſaults on it, and to eraze it with the Divine aſſiſtance, which we muſt not fail to implore with much ardour and perſeverance, and having obtained it, to imploy it with force and courage againſt the perverſe tendencies of our deſires, this to be ſure we muſt do if we would not periſh Eternally. It is on this account that JESUS CHRIST layes, that <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth violence, and that the violent take it by force. Matt:</hi> 11.12. However we muſt even here uſe diſcretion; Yet not ſuch as is carnal or humane, but a diſcretion that is Spiritual and Divine, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from above, and which therefore we ought ardently to demand of GOD, on whoſe direction the conduct of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing our own will, ought alſo to depend.]</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>12. 2.</hi> Conſequence to entertain low &amp; mean thoughts of our ſelves, never deſiring the praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of men which young ones muſt be taught to ſlight and deſpiſe.</note>§. 12. 2. Since that none can do any good of himſelf and without GOD, and that all our own deſires are corrupt, therefore <hi>we muſt not deſire to be Eſteemed, Honoured, and Praiſed by any perſon, neither
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179950:25"/>
muſt we be conceited of our ſelves,</hi> but deſire that men take us for what we really are; that is to ſay, for poor nothings, and for ſinful &amp; depraved creatures.</p>
               <p>This is that <hi>Humility,</hi> which is a door by which the Grace of GOD enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Soul, according to the Scripture, which ſayes, that <hi>God gives Grace to the Humble:</hi> 1 Pet: 5.5.</p>
               <p>O would to God, that Young Ones were trained up to this betimes, and without interruption, inſtead of being educated after that Antichriſtian and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolical manner, in which Men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly bring them up, as well in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, as publick Schools, and even eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where elſe, in breathing and pouring into their hearts on all occaſions, the mortal poyſon of praiſes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, which ſerve for no other uſe, but to plant in them a fatal pride, which makes them the enemies of God, according to that word of St. <hi>Peter</hi> I chap, 5. verſe 5. <hi>God reſiſts the proud,</hi> and that other of <hi>Solomon, The proud in heart are an Abomination to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">§. 13. 3.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>§. 13. 3.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the leſt &amp; worſt of things a leſſon which Young Ones muſt be carefully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in.</note> A Creature which of it ſelf is but nothing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179950:26"/>
and ſin, and therefore is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to believe that it me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits nothing, <hi>ought to be content even when it hath nothing, or but very little, and ought not to deſire more then that which it hath, but to take for its uſe, of all things the left and leſs worthy.</hi> Believing that theſe are ſtill but <hi>too good for a nothing, and for a Sinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is it which it were better to make Young Ones underſtand and practiſe, then unhappily to ſtudy, as commonly people do, to ſtir up and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waken in their hearts, by a thouſand pernicious inventions, all ſorts of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſes, to attire them pompouſly, and flatter all their Senſes the moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably that is poſſible, never refuſing them any thing that may contribute to make them the ſlaves of the fleſh, of vanity and of corruption, and ſo to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them very early as Antichriſtian as the devil could deſire.</p>
               <p>[The neglect of this Rule, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the two foregoing, as well as the practice of the contrary; are the foundations of Antichriſtianiſm; as the Obſervance of them is the ſame thing with the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179950:26"/>
Foundations of true Chriſtianity: Therefore it is that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſayes, that whoſoever will not deny himſelf, cannot be his Diſciple. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. and 14, 26.]</p>
               <p>§. 14. 3.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>§. 14. 3.</hi> How to kindle Pious and Divine Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations towards God in the hearts of Young Ones.</note>When the deſire is thus turned from evil, it is with the greater eaſe turned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, to whom alone we ought to addreſs and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote theſe tender hearts, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to make good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and inclinations towards their Creatour, to ſpring up in them, at the occaſion and by the conſideration of all ſorts of things.</p>
               <p>§. 15. 1. From the conſideration of God as He is in himſelf Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Goodneſs, Beauty and Felicity it ſelf, they muſt be excited and prompted to the deſire of eſteeming Him, of praiſing Him, of honouring Him as He deſerves, and of pleaſing Him in every thing. They muſt be made to underſtand that it is principally for this that we are ſent into the World, namely, that we may eſteem, honour and praiſe God without end, by the deſires and continual Elevations of our hearts to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179950:27"/>
Him; and that ſince this is the Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Angels, by being exerciſed in it we become their companions in this World, and even fellow Citizens of Heaven with them, in imitating ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lily theſe Divine Spirits, who ſing eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before GOD, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God of Hoſts, the whole Earth is full of Thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Iſa: 6.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>16, 2.</hi> From the conſideration of the Benefites of GOD both paſt &amp; preſent.</note>§. 16. 2. With reſpect to the Benefits of God, when w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall repreſent unto them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all comes from Him, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Soul, our Body, our Life our Parents, our Friends, the Good Angels which he ſends to defend us, the Earth on which we walk the Air which we breath, the Sun which enlightens us, the meats which Nouriſh us, the cloaths which cover us, the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which warms us; We muſt awaken i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them on all theſe occaſions &amp; every day the deſire of being Gratefull toward God, and thanking Him for all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of theſe things, as often as they ſhall have occaſion to ſerve themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of them. If one ought to make Grate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful returns to a mortal Man when he does us good, much more ought we to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179950:27"/>
make them unto <hi>God;</hi> who both hath made that Man, and doth us good by him. Thus it is that the Bleſſed Ones above pay their Acknowledgements to Him, <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord our God, to receive Glory, and Honour, and Power: For Thou haſt created all things, and for Thy pleaſure they are, and were created.</hi> Rev. 4.11.</p>
               <p>GOD hath not only beſtowed on us good things throughout what is paſt of our life, but he ſtill purſues us with a continual reiteration of his bleſſings; For without his goodneſs, both we and all the World, would fall every moment into confuſion and ruin, juſt as a brittle Veſſal, if it were not ever, and without intermiſſion ſupported by ſomething, would fall and be broken in pieces; And therefore, our deſire and our heart ought alwayes to be diſpoſed, to thank and pay continual homages unto GOD for his continual bleſſings, according to that exhortation of St. <hi>Paul, Giving thanks alwayes for all things unto GOD, and the Father, in the name of our LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST. Eph:</hi> 5.20.</p>
               <p n="17">§. 17. 3. And becauſe we have need of his good things for the time to come,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>17. 3.</hi> From the expectation of future bleſſings, eſpecially of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual ones.</note> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179950:28"/>
of Spiritual Bleſſings if we would be happy, and ſince he will give them to ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall deſire them truely in their hearts, we muſt above all thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt diligently labour to diſpoſe young ones to lift up their <hi>deſires</hi> to GOD, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeek from him his Grace, his good Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit, the Knowledge of Himſelf, true Vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue; An Heart that is ſincere, humble obedient, ſweet, content in every ſtate tender and grateful towards GOD <hi>If any man lake Wiſdom,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James</hi> 1.5. <hi>Let him ask it of GOD, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> giveth it to all liberally, and it ſhall be give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">§. 18. That we may o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain theſe and the like grace we deſire from this Soveraig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Benefactor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>18.</hi> that our deſires may be ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful, great care muſt be taken to do the will of GOD.</note> we muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber to be ſolicitouſly careful, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to offend him from whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expect ſuch great favours; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be alwayes ready to do h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will; <hi>For GOD heareth not ſinners, but any man be a worſhipper of GOD, and do his will, him he heareth,</hi> ſaith the Goſpel <hi>Jo:</hi> 9: 21.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:179950:28"/>§. 19. 4. But ſince we have often offended in the time paſt of our life,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>19. 4.</hi> From the conſideration of paſt ſins.</note> and ſo are unworthy of his grace and of his favours, we muſt with an ardent deſire intreat him for the pardon of our paſt offences, as alſo beſeech him to preſerve us from them in time to come.</p>
               <p n="20">§. 20. Theſe four ſorts of deſires; I, To praiſe GOD,<note place="margin">20. The nature, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of Prayer.</note> and his infinite per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; 2, To be thankful to him for his favours; 3, To ſeek his Divine grace in order to pleaſe him; And 4, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his mercies, for the pardon of our ſins, do make up that which we call <hi>Prayer.</hi> We never in effect Pray unto GOD, but when we have truely and ſincerely ſuch deſires as theſe in our hearts, without which although we teach young ones all the vocal Prayers in the World, we do make but Parats of them, and ſuch whereof GOD ſayes, <hi>This people draweth nigh to me with the mouth, but their hearts</hi> (or deſires) <hi>are farr from Me. Iſa.</hi> a0.9.</p>
               <p n="21">[§. 21. We muſt not on this occaſion be unmindful to make young ones under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>21.</hi> What pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt imports.</note> that when they are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179950:29"/>
taught according to the injunction of Holy Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pture, to addreſs all their Prayers to GOD in the <hi>Name of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> in order to be heard of their Heavenly Father, the meaning is not that they muſt ſimply pronounce the ſound and the ſyllables of the <hi>Name of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST;</hi> If this were ſo the moſt part of the Prayers recorded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf, ſhould not be made in the Name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> But the import of the injunction is, that we muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire by the <hi>Grace,</hi> and by the Virtue of JESUS CHRIST, and have deſires wholly conform and like unto his, to the end that Jeſus Chriſt acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as having ſprung from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, may unite them unto his own and offer them as his own deſires unto GOD his Father, and that the Father who cannot refuſe any thing to the deſires, and to the merits of his well beloved Son; and who grants him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes his deſires, may alſo grant us ours, as being included in his; Yea, and even making a part of them: So that when one ſayes to GOD, <hi>hear us O LORD! In the name of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, or I beſeech thee in the Name of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> it is as much as if one did
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179950:29"/>
                  <q>ſay unto him, "I offer unto thee O LORD, theſe ſame deſires which the grace of Jeſus Chriſt doth inſpire me withall, and which I will not mingle with the deſires of my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, but conform them, and unite them unto the deſires of thy Son, to the end that thou mayeſt have reſpect unto them in him, and that by this means thou mayeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh them for his ſake, to thy Glory and my Salvation.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="22">§. 22. It appears now from all theſe important Truths,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>22.</hi> A ſerious Endeavour to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in Young Ones an habit of lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their hearts to GOD frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerly, is the firſt and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt concern of their Education.</note> that the firſt and capital work of the Education we are treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of is, to teach Young Ones to lift up their Deſires towards GOD on all Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by little ſighs and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, conform to the Will of GOD, and ſo ſimple, as that with the Divine Grace they may fitly come from themſelves: As for Inſtance, to train them to ſay according to the different Occaſions,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>My GOD, who art all Good, all Wiſe, and Almighty, be Thou bleſſed for ever.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:179950:30"/>
                  <q>Grant me the Grace to love Thee, and to obey Thee.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I give Thee thanks, becauſe thou haſt created and redeemed me.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>My GOD I praiſe Thee, that Thou haſt created the World and all that is in it, becauſe Thou gives me food and raiment, becauſe Thou wilt give me Eternal Good Things, and becauſe Thou wilt come to dwell in my Soul, and take Thy delights with me Eternally.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>My GOD deliver me from my ſins, give me Thy good Spirit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Give me the Grace that I may never love to do mine own will, but only Thy Will.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>My LORD, grant that I may have an humble heart, that I may not eſteem my ſelf better then others, but that rather I may deſpiſe my ſelf, and account my ſelf to be below all the Creatures.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Make me to hate and to eſchew the praiſes and flatteries of men; Thou only ought to be praiſed, for Thou only art the cauſe of all the Good which we can ever do.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Give me to be alwayes content with every thing that befals me. I do not deſerve but hell, and the leaſt of all Thy Mercies, as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:179950:30"/>
indeed the meaneſt of all things, are ſtill much more then I deſerve.</q>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe kinds of Elevations, when Young Ones are daily accuſtomed to them, the ſolide Principles of true Chriſtianity, and the living Seed of Life Eternal are planted in their Souls.</p>
               <p n="23">§. 23. We may do well alſo to make them learn by Heart ſome Holy Vocal Prayers, and above all,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>23.</hi> That it is neceſſary to teach Young Ones Vocal Prayers, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all they muſt be told that theſe are not prayers, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Heart act its part in them.</note> 
                  <hi>The LORDS Prayer,</hi> which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Himſelf hath preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us. But withal, we muſt carefully inculcate on them, that it is not a Prayer, and that it is not agreeable unto GOD, but when the Heart hath truely in it, the <hi>Deſire</hi> that GOD ſhould be 1. Eſteemed and Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; 2. Honoured and Praiſed; 3. Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; 4. That he would nouriſh our Souls with His Grace and with His Love. 5. That He would deliver us from our paſt ſins. And 6. That He would preſerve us from them for the future, as well as from the innumerable and hidden ſnares, by which the Devil endeavours
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179950:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to make us fall into them, which are the ſix or ſeven Petitions of this Prayer, to which we may joyn that which is at the end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<note n="*" place="margin">It is to be found at the end of this Letter.</note> of the Works of <hi>Rus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brochius;</hi> As alſo ſome of the Pſalms of <hi>David;</hi> But in the mean time, we muſt let them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that when we pray there againſt our Enemies, and when we deſire that GOD would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate them,<note place="margin">A needful Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations that are in the Pſalms.</note> this muſt be underſtood in a Spiritual Manner, That is to ſay, of the Spiritual and true enemies of our Souls, which are our ſins, and our vices, our ſelf-will, our ſelf love, our pride, our vanity, in one word, our old man, of which we ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from the LORD the ruine and extermination, otherwiſe, we ſhould change the Pſalms into pernicious poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in applying the Imprecations that are in them to our Neighbour, whom we ought to love.</p>
               <p>[We may alſo very profitably imploy the Imprecations of the Pſalms, and the ardent Prayer that are there made, that GOD would confound, deſtroy and root out our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179950:31"/>
againſt the evil ſpirits, our mortal and inviſible enemies, who, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſayes, <hi>Go round about us like roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lions, ſeeking to devour us,</hi> 1 Pet. 5: 8. And who by their fiery darts, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.16. That is to ſay, by their villan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inſpirations, endeavour to kindle in us all ſorts of wicked deſires, and ſinful inclinations, that they may make us periſh eternally. When we find our ſelves tempted to evil, eſpecially when it is againſt our will, theſe ſorts of Pſalms and Prayers againſt the tempter and enemie of our Souls, come in very ſeaſonably, and are the true weapons of our defence.]</p>
               <p n="24">§. 24.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>24.</hi> Parents muſt make up the defects and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Infancie by their own ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Piety and Devotions, for which GOD will be ſure to reward them, and bleſs their Off-ſpring.</note> In fine becauſe that Young Ones have as yet their Faculties almoſt all aſleep, and but very little Active, it will be neceſſary here, that their Parents come to their Aſſiſtance, and ſupply their Impotency and all theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as well in turning from evil their own deſires, as in offering alwayes to GOD, in behalf of their Children, theſe ſame Holy deſires, and theſe true
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179950:32"/>
and genuine Prayers, whereof we have ſpoken. For GOD accepting then the deſires of Fathers and Mothers in Name and behalf of, and as coming from their Children, and being willing to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe the Piety of the Parents, He will not fail to anſwer them, by the ſaving Operations of his Good Spirit on the hearts of all their poſterity, and ſo <hi>Shewing Mercy unto thouſand Generations of thoſe that love Him, Exod:</hi> 20:6.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>25.</hi> The ſad Conſequences of not beginning the Education of young Ones from the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of their deſire.</note>§. 25. The Improvement of the <hi>Deſire</hi> or of the <hi>heart</hi> of Young Ones, is a point ſo fundamental, and ſo eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to their Good Education, that if we either abſolutely neglect this, or if we do not begin their Inſtruction by it, but by things which only concern their Underſtanding, we cannot chooſe but miſerably ruine their Souls, in leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them, and even planting in them by this negligence, the fatall ſeeds of Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion, of Spiritual careleſneſs, of forgetfulneſs, and diſreſpect of GOD, of vanity, of pride, in a word, of death Eternal. Notwithſtanding this is it whereof Men do but little think: <hi>The
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179950:32"/>
whole World,</hi> ſaith St. John, <hi>lyeth in wickedneſs,</hi> and that we may not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the miſerable World in this point, it can be never enough recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to thoſe who would educat their Children Chriſtianly, not ſo much to cultivat their mind, as to make their heart. 1. Pious towards GOD. 2. Humble in themſelves. 3 Meek and Charitable towards their Neighbour. And 4. Content, with regard to all that which may happen them, and which may be done unto them: On ſuch a Foundation as this GOD builds great things, and even takes in his Hand the whole conduct of the Soul.</p>
               <p n="26">§. 26. 11.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>26. 11.</hi> Truth that is God his word &amp; works the object of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</note> The ſecond and the principal of the Faculties of our Souls, is the power of <hi>Knowing,</hi> or our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath been made for the <hi>Truth,</hi> that is to ſay for God himſelf who is the Truth, and for his Word and his Works; which are the ſtreams of this Soveraign and Original Truth.</p>
               <p n="27">§. 27.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>27.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of this.</note> And ſo we ought not to deſire to know any thing but God, and that which he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179950:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hath ſaid and done for His Glory.</p>
               <p n="28">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>28. 1.</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence a lie and whatever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Truth, depraves the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and muſt not be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Children</note>§. 28. 1. And therefore falſhood, or a lye, which is oppoſite to Truth, is the moſt abominable of all things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it corrupts and perverts the moſt noble of the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our Soul? we ought not to tolerat it in the leaſt in young ones, nor ſuffer them to unpuniſhed, when they bewray in any meaſure this diabolical enormity, <hi>the devil being</hi> (which is the firſt and chief of all his qualities) <hi>a liar, and the father of lies;</hi> ſaith the Scripture.</p>
               <p n="29">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>29. 2.</hi> We muſt not ſtuff our minds with the knowledge of uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs things, but ſeaſonably check our vain curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note>§. 29. 2. For the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we ought not to apply our ſelves to the knowledge of the unprofitable diſcourſes, vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, inventions, cnimeras and fictions, and the deeds of vain and corrupted Men, we muſt betimes reſiſt curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſitie and diſtraction which fill the mind with obſcuritie and darkneſs, and render it inſenſible and unſuitable to ſolid Truth and to the Light of God, how great a loſs it is to fill with dirt and impurities a precious
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:179950:33"/>
veſſel, which was made for no other end, but to lodge and contain God and his moſt pure Lights, which are incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible with the impure fictions of the depraved minds of corrupted and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men.</p>
               <p n="30">§. 30.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>30.</hi> How the faculty of knowing is exerciſed in Man.</note> The faculty of knowing is exerciſed in Man, 1. By the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> or the <hi>Pure Mind,</hi> 2. By <hi>reaſon.</hi> 3. By the <hi>Imagination</hi> aſſiſted by the Senſes, eſpecially theſe of Seeing and Hearing.</p>
               <p n="31">§. 31. 1.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>31. 1.</hi> The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding ſince the Fall is blind as to Divine things, GOD only can cure this blindneſs, of both which Young Ones muſt be early made ſenſible.</note> The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> or the <hi>Pure Mind,</hi> which is deſigned for Divine Things, is intirely ſhut up in all men ſince the entrance of ſin.</p>
               <p>We are, and are born all blind as to Divine Things, and it is God only that is able to heal, to open and to enlighten the eye of our Soul, ſo as to capacitat us to know Spiritual Things.</p>
               <p>As we could not ſee nor know the Sun, the Earth, the Trees, nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things of this World, if GOD had not given us bodily eyes; So neither
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179950:34"/>
can we able ever to know the things of GOD, if he do not reſtore to our Soul its Spiritual Eves which it hath broken, and which GOD doth not reim part no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> open, but to thoſe only whoſe Heart i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> withdrawn from ſin, and inclined and carried to good.</p>
               <p>This ought to be inculcate on al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from their Infancy, to the end that the mind may tend betimes towards GOD, and that by the Goodneſs of its Deſires and Purity of Heart, it may be diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his Divine Light; For GOD doth not diſcover his Secrets, but to ſuch as fear to do evil, and he gives not his Light, but to thoſe who will make a good uſe of it, as <hi>David,</hi> who ſaid to him, <hi>Give me, O LORD, the underſtanding of thy Law, and I ſhall keep it, yea, I ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it with my whole Heart, Pſal:</hi> 119.34</p>
               <p n="32">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>32.</hi> We muſt believe what we do not yet Divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee.</note>§. 32. As long as GOD hath not yet opened the Eye of our Soul, to ſee by his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine &amp; ſupernatural Light the Things above, the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Myſteries and Truths of our Religion, it is neceſſary that we believe, though we do not yet ſee all that GOD hath ſaid to us of them, or all that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:179950:34"/>
which the Saints who have the Spirit of GOD have told us of them; But we muſt not believe what the Men of the World talk of them, for they are blind and liars. In this <hi>every man</hi> (who hath not the Spirit of GOD) <hi>is a liar,</hi> ſaid <hi>David, Pſal:</hi> 116.11.</p>
               <p n="33">§. 33. This is the Principle, or ground work of <hi>Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>33.</hi> The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and Light of Faith.</note> Namely, to believe and rely on that which GOD hath revealed to us of Divine Things, which we do not as yet ſee, and which we do not underſtand, in the mean time waiting patiently, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that he would open unto us the Eyes of the Mind, and give us his Light, that by it we may ſee clearly when it ſhall pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>This Light being come into the Soul is called <hi>The clear Light of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[But when we have not as yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained particular &amp; clear diſcoverie of Divine Things, and that nevertheleſs we believe them, in confideing to the Teſtimonie and to the Conduct of GOD blindly, and without compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending any thing in them, this is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Obſcuritie</hi> or the <hi>dark light of Faith,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:179950:35"/>
which oftentimes is the moſt ſure and moſt ſaving for us, as being leſs ſubject to preſumption and to pride: To this may be applyed that Word of the Son is of GOD, <hi>Bleſſed are they that have not ſeen, and yet have believed, Joh:</hi> 20.29]</p>
               <p n="34">§. 34. 11. Although Young Ones be incapable to make uſe of <hi>Reaſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>34. 11.</hi> Young Ones are to be guarded againſt the abuſe &amp; deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of corrupted Reaſon.</note> much leſs of <hi>Reaſoning,</hi> we muſt neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs endeavour, as ſoon as if poſſible, to inculcate on them a Principle which will ſecure them from the Impoſtures, and the Idolatrie of humane reaſon, which is the grand evil, the capital and common Idol, And the almoſt univerſal Atheiſm of this Age, eſpecially among thoſe who make profeſſion of Learning and Science.</p>
               <p n="35">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>35.</hi> How this may be beſt done, is declared by a ſignificant compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon.</note>§. 35. This Principle may be rendred intelligible unto them by this compariſon. That as a blind man, though he may think and diſcourſe, and reaſon the beſt in the World, yet can he not by that mean either know or ſee either the Sun or other Creatures, for at this rate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179950:35"/>
he could not have but dark thoughts, groſs and wholly falſe apprehenſions of them; Juſt ſo, though all the men of the World ſhould think, diſcourſe, and reaſon of Divine Things, by all the force of their Spirit, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they could not know by that mean, either GOD, or the Things of GOD; But only have wholly dark, and even wholly impertinent thoughts of them. It will be neceſſarie that <hi>GOD,</hi> to the end he may be well known, give other Eyes to the Mind, as alſo another Light then that which comes to us from our own activity; and as long as he doth not give them Humane Reaſon, with reſpect to Spiritual Things, is nothing but a very ſhop of ridiculous Chimera's, and the pure Fictions of blind Men.</p>
               <p n="36">§. 36. But further (that we may continue our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon) as when we have made a Sun or fruits in Effigie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>36.</hi> The diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted reaſon makes of Divine things are lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guid, faint, &amp; in effectual</note> theſe pictures of the Sun and of the fruits cannot enlighten us, nor warm us, nor nouriſh us, nor give us any ſtrength or vigor, ſo as the true Sun and the real Fruits do; Juſt ſo, though
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179950:36"/>
by our reaſon we repreſent unto our ſelves God, and Virtue, and Divine things, yet theſe Ideas, theſe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, and theſe diſcourſes of our Reaſons touching God, and the things of GOD, cannot at all give us true Lights, nor true Virtue, nor adminiſter nouriſhment and ſtrength to our Souls to live according to God, and to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe his Divine Will. Theſe are but cold, empty, lifeleſs and wholly bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and unfruitful images, on which we cannot raiſe any other ſuperſtructure, but wind and vanity, which ſerve to no other purpoſe, but to puff up the minds of Men, and which put them in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, the one againſt the other, by diſſentions, by diſputes, and by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual combats, until ſuch time as they burſt of themſelves, or ſplit one againſt another.</p>
               <p n="37">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>37.</hi> That the ſpirit of Man without the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of GOD cannot diſcern Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things is a truth that betimes muſt be ſetled and ever cheriſhed in all hearts.</note>§. 37. To prevent theſe inconveniencies, behold the principal which we ought to ingrave betimes, and preſerve tenderly in all hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Spirit or reaſon of Man, without the grace or ſupernatural light of GOD, is but a blind man
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179950:36"/>
which makes vain and fantaſtick images of things which it hath not ſeen, and which it can never ſee. The natural man,</hi> ſaith <hi>St. Paul, cannot know the things of GOD; He holds them for fooliſhneſs, and he cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them, beeauſe they are known by a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual light. No man knows the things of GOD, but the Spirit of GOD, and he who hath received this Spirit.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.11, 12, 14.</p>
               <p n="38">§. 38. We muſt not then ſo much,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>38.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore renouncing the dark and glimmering noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our own reaſon, we muſt in ardent Prayers offer up our inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous and evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated ſouls to GOD to be Enlightened by him.</note> and with ſuch ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous care, endeavour to cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate and dreſs our mind, by our own force and by our own induſtrie, as to turn it away from the fictions of our reaſonings, and from vanity, and offer it up to GOD in ſimplicity, and wholly emptied and naked, with a vehement deſire to do his will alone, and with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Prayers, beſeeching him to give unto us his light, &amp; to open our eyes; For ſaith the Scripture, <hi>It is GOD that gives eyes to the blind, that opens them to ſee the wonders of his Law and of his will, and enlightens the eyes of our underſtanding. Pſal:</hi> 146. and 119. <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="39">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:179950:37"/>§. 39. If we would never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs exerciſe in ſome ſort the <hi>reaſon</hi> of young Ones,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>39.</hi> The right method of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing the reaſon of Young Ones, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended and illuſtrated by ſome inſtances.</note> as in effect this we may, and ought to do, and if we incline to make them underſtand things by reaſons, or oblidge them to give a reaſon of any thing that we would, we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom them to give on every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Divine reaſons; My meaning is, reaſons drawn from the Power of GOD, from his Wiſdom, from his Goodneſs, from his Juſtice, from his Will, from his Felicity, from his Glory, as alſo from our own nothingneſs, from our weakneſs, from our own injuſtice, wickedneſs, ignorance, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>For example, wherefore did GOD Creat the World? To manifeſt his <hi>Power,</hi> his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and his <hi>Goodneſs.</hi> Wherefore did he make Man? For that very ſame end, and withall to ſhew him, and give him his <hi>Felicity,</hi> and his <hi>Glory.</hi> Wherefore doth man die? By the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of GOD; It being <hi>Juſt,</hi> that ſince man did abuſe his life, it ſhould be taken from him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are the good afflicted by ſickneſs, or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179950:37"/>
any other way? Becauſe ſince they have been formerly guilty of ſome ſins, the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of GOD ſo orders it, that they ſhould be rather corrected for them in this temporal life, then in the other which is Eternal. Wherefore on the other hand doth good oftentimes befal the wicked here below? By the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of GOD, who ſweetly invites them to his love, or alſo by his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> who will give them in this life the recompence of any little good they may have done in it; Whereas in the other life they ſhall be Eternally puniſhed for the ſins in which they have lived without forſaking them; And ſo as to all other things, even the moſt material and viſible. We muſt make them underſtand, for example, that wars fall out, becauſe that GOD is <hi>Juſt,</hi> and that men and their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deſerve to be puniſhed; We muſt tell them that the fire is warm, by the reaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that GOD is good, and that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that man hath need of heat, that he may live, he hath by his goodneſs given him the fire with ſuch a quality, that the fire burns and cauſes pain, by the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of GOD, who makes uſe of this creature, as a Rod for the chaſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179950:38"/>
of men who have ſinned; And as to moral things we ought to do the ſame, and tell them for inſtance, that we muſt obey our Parents and Superiors in this and in that, becauſe it is the <hi>will</hi> of GOD: That we muſt not value our ſelves, nor deſire that others ſhould eſteem us, becauſe GOD only deſerves that, as being only <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and only <hi>good</hi> and that we are but <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> but <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> but <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of our ſelves, that we muſt not wiſh nor render evil to thoſe who do evil to us, becauſe GOD wills that we ſhould do as he doth who alwayes doth us good, and even then when we offend him, that we muſt not diſeſteem, Judge nor diſhonour our Neighbour, becauſe GOD alone will be his judge, and that it is his <hi>Will</hi> that we ſhould love others as our ſelves, that we are too <hi>ignorant</hi> to know the hearts of others, and too <hi>perverſe</hi> to Judge favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably of them, or without paſſion, and ſo of the reſt.</p>
               <p n="40">
                  <note place="margin">40. The happy advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</note>§. 40 If we did imploy every day ſome moments, to exerciſe, after this manner, the reaſon of young Ones, we would very ſoon accuſtom them to ſee GOD in every thing, to have him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179950:38"/>
before their eyes, and to walk continually as in his preſence. There is nothing in this World, whether Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, Humane, Natural or Political, Hiſtories, whether Sacred or prophane, whereof we might not very eaſily make them reduce all the cauſes, and all the particular events with their reaſons to theſe admirable Principles of the <hi>Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, truth, Juſtice, Felicity, Glory, Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> and to the <hi>weakneſs, ignorance, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie,</hi> and <hi>malignitie of Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This, beſides that, it would render GOD alwayes preſent to us, would moreover wonderfully ſerve to rectifie reaſon after a moſt ſolid and ſaving manner, providing that we did it, implor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſincerity and humility, the Grace and Bleſſing of GOD.</p>
               <p>We might begin to make ſome <hi>Eſſay</hi> of it on an Hiſtory of the Scripture; For inſtance, on the Hiſtorie of the ſelling of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> which is in the Book of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> or on ſome Hiſtorical Chapter of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="41">§. 41. III. Since the <hi>Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ination,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>41. III.</hi> The imaginatione of Young Ones muſt be early improven.</note> as well as the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie,</hi> is that which hath moſt ſtrength, and moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179950:39"/>
in Young Ones, we ſhall do well to improve them very ſoon; that by this way alſo, we may commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate unto them as much of the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of the things of their Salvation as is poſſible, and as they are then capable of.</p>
               <p n="42">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>42.</hi> A neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie caution. All the notices of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things, which we receive by the imagination are but verie dark and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect images.</note>§. 42. But it is good to let them underſtand before hand, that <hi>all the knowledge they ſhall acquire after this manner, is but very groſs and very obſcure Pictures of Divine things,</hi> whereof they do not know by that the hundred thouſandth part, not even the leaſt part as realie it is in it ſelf, becauſe that the things of GOD have by millions of times more perfections then we are able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend of them, untill that in proceſs of time, and after that we have conſtantly prayed unto GOD, and done his will, he diſpel and chaſe away our groſs and dull way of knowing, and then make us ſee the pure beautie of his truth.</p>
               <p>This ſhall hinder theſe little Spirits from curuing their firſt thoughts unto obſtinate prejudices; and it will diſpoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:179950:39"/>
them to teachableneſs, and to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the Light of GOD.</p>
               <p n="43">§. 43.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>43.</hi> This may be exerciſed in Young Ones three wayes. <hi>1</hi> By read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and leting them ſee the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred hiſtories.</note> We may exerciſe their minds in this reſpect. 1. By reading, and even by the ſight of ſome repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Hiſtories of the Holy Scripture, to the end that ſo their memorie, and their imagination may be filled, with Holy Images.</p>
               <p>And we muſt at the ſame time accuſtom them to reduce that which they ſhall read or ſee, at leaſt the principal heads, to the Divine principles which we have alreadie recommended.</p>
               <p n="44">§. 44. 2. By the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Creed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>44. 2.</hi> By ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them with the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and meaning of the Belief.</note> which they ought to learn by heart, and on which we ought to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with them according to their capacitie. 1. Of GOD the Father and the Creatour, of his Perfections, Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and the reſt, of his Works, as well Spiritual as Corporal, as well theſe that are dureable and Eternal, as theſe that are Temporal and tranſient. 2. Of GOD Incarnat, or of the Son of GOD, JESUS CHRIST,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179950:40"/>
of his works which concern our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, And 3. of the Holy Spirit, whoſe works regard the reſtitution of man to his firſt Eſtate.</p>
               <p n="45">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>45.</hi> Where three things muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to their notices.</note>§. 45. And on this head it will be profitable to oblige them to remarke two or three things of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> GODS Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious deſigns and conduct with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to man both in his Creation and Redemption, which is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the whole.</note>One is, that all that is in the <hi>Creed</hi> doth iſſue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult in this principle, <hi>Viz.</hi> that GOD the Almighty, and the Creator of all things did make man, to the end that man turning all his <hi>deſires,</hi> and his will towards his GOD, GOD ſhould fill his mind with his Divine knowledge, and his Soul with His Joy and with His Felicitie and Eternal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but man having turned away his <hi>deſire</hi> and his will from GOD, and ſo having rendred his mind ignorant, and his Soul unhappy and miſerable for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, GOD did aſſume our humane nature, and live and die amongſt us, not only to merit for us the pardon of our wickedneſs, and the Divine Grace,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:179950:40"/>
but alſo to demonſtrate unto us by his Doctrine, and by the examples of his Life, of his Death, and of his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how we ought to renounce our evil <hi>deſires,</hi> to forſake and make to ceaſe and die our own will, and to reſume new and Divine <hi>deſires,</hi> a will Holy and living unto GOD, the which the Holy Spirit imparts unto the ſoul, together with an illuminated <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and a Divine <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> whereby we are reunited with all that which is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as well on Earth as in Heaven, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying in this Holy Society and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, the Spiritual Grace and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of JESUS CHRIST here in time, to the end, that after the death of the body, and then after its Reſurrection, we may live together Eternalie and Gloriouſly with GOD.</p>
               <p n="46">§. 46. 2. A ſecond thing which we ought to oblige them particularly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>46. 2.</hi> Another thing they muſt be made ſeriouſly to obſerve, is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of Jeſus Chriſt in our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie as deſigned for our imitation.</note> is how JESUS CHRIST in His Birth, in His Actions, in His Life, and His Death, hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged and conducted the faculties of his Soul, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179950:41"/>
particularly his <hi>deſires</hi> and his <hi>Will,</hi> as well in turning them from evil, from the natural inclinations of our mortal humanitie, from the eſteem of himſelf from the ſearch of pleaſures, of the commodities and good things of this World, by ſelf denyal, by diſgrace, by lowneſs, by povertie, by ſufferings and an unrepining acquieſcence in all, as in turning and yeelding unto GOD theſe ſame <hi>Deſires</hi> and will of his, not deſiring any thing but GOD, doing nothing but his Divine will in every thing, and adhering alwayes to him by praiſes, and continual Prayer, by which his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> obtained all the Divine Lights which he demanded of his Father, in whoſe good pleaſure he alſo placed all his Joy.</p>
               <p n="47">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>47.</hi> They muſt be taught that the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghoſt mentioned in the Belief are but one GOD, and that this Glorious myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible.</note>§. 47. We may in the third place, on the ſubject of the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> tell them in a few words, that the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> whereof mention is made in the <hi>Belief,</hi> and in the Scripture, are not but <hi>One</hi> only and the ſame GOD, as in us (to give ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:179950:41"/>
of this great Myſtrie) the <hi>deſire,</hi> the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and the <hi>Joy</hi> or pleaſure of the Soul, are but one only Soul and not three. That the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that is among them, doth not hinder the Unity of the Divine Nature, which is the ſame, and one in all, but that this difference is ſuch in GOD, that no reaſon nor humane light neither can, nor ought to endeavour to comprehend it; That we muſt believe it with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence on the Teſtimony of the word of GOD, without knowing it otherwayes waiting untill it pleaſe GOD to make us ſee ſomething of it that will be more clear, whether in this life or the other, and in the mean time, contenting our ſelves to repreſent unto us according to our weak capacity, <hi>GOD the Father</hi> as the <hi>Author</hi> of all good things, the <hi>Father and Juſt Judge</hi> of our Souls; <hi>GOD the Son</hi> as the <hi>Redeemer</hi> of the World, and the <hi>inlightener</hi> of our Souls, that are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and fallen into darkneſs, and the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> as <hi>GOD</hi> the <hi>Sanctifier</hi> of hearts and filling with the love of GOD the Souls which had been corrupted by ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, and by ſin: Or yet moreover, <hi>GOD</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> as <hi>good, and the principle
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:179950:42"/>
of goodneſs,</hi> who hath Created all things by the communication of his goodneſs: GOD the Son as <hi>Juſt, and the principle</hi> of Juſtice, who was incarnat to render us Juſt, who were made unjuſt by ſin. GOD the Holy Ghoſt as the <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> who opens, and who illuminates the mind, that it may comprehend the truth of Spiritual and Divine things.</p>
               <p n="48">
                  <note place="margin">48. What it is to know the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in a Divine &amp; ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer.</note>[§. 48. In fine, they ought to be made remember on this occaſion, that the true knowledge of Divine things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the living operations of the Holy Spirit in the inward man, as hath been already aſſerted, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the knowledge of the Holy Trinity, to the end that it may be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and ſaving, muſt be produced by him in us after the ſame manner; And ſuch it ſhall certainly be, if this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge iſſues in a living repreſentation of the moſt Holy Trinitie (after the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of which we were likewiſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) as alſo if the ſame knowledge ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates and reſults in the love and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of GOD, ſo vigorouſly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by St. <hi>Paul, Be ye followers of GOD, as being his dear Children, and walk in love even as CHRIST hath loved us.</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:179950:42"/>
Eph. 5.1, 2. <hi>For every one that loveth,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John, is born of GOD, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth GOD; But he that loveth not, knoweth not GOD,</hi> (nor conſequently the Holy Trinity) <hi>for GOD is love,</hi> 1 Joh: 4.7, 8. So that, <hi>whoſoever ſaith that he knoweth JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, and keepeth not his Commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him,</hi> ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, Chap 2. <hi>V.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>So then, an infallible mark that we truely know the Holy Trinity, and that we confeſs ſavingly the <hi>Father, the Creator, the good and the powerful,</hi> is, when we love him with fear, obedience and reſpect, when we confidently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign our ſelves to his Power and divine providence, and when we repreſent, and follow his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> towards all, and in every thing.</p>
               <p>We know and confeſs ſavingly <hi>the Son the Redeemer, and the Juſt one,</hi> when we live as being <hi>delivered by him from this preſent evil world. Gal:</hi> 1.4. And when we give up our ſelves to <hi>the practice of Righteouſneſs.</hi> 1 Joh: 2.29.</p>
               <p>And we know and confeſs ſavingly, the <hi>Holy Spirit, the Sanctifier, and the Spirit of Truth,</hi> when we give up our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179950:43"/>
ſelves <hi>to Holineſs, without which none ſhall ſee</hi> (nor conſequently ever know livingly) <hi>the LORD. Heb.</hi> 12.14. And when <hi>we follow the truth in Love. Eph.</hi> 4.15.</p>
               <p>Such a knowledge of the Holy Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as this is, is not an ideal operation of our Humane Reaſon; but a true and real production of the Holy Spirit, ſince the <hi>fruits of the Spirit,</hi> ſaith St. Paul, <hi>are goodneſs, Righteouſneſs and Truth.</hi> Eph. 5.9.</p>
               <p>But when we reject either all theſe things, or even ſome of them, we do then in effect deny GOD and his Divine Trinity, which we do not confeſs, but with the mouth only, or by ſome vain and dead acts of barren reaſon, ſo as the Devil himſelf doth; <hi>ſuch</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, profeſs to know GOD</hi> (and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Trinity) but nevertheleſs they do effectually deny him by their works, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.]</p>
               <p n="49">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>49. III.</hi> The imagination of Young Ones may be entertained with Emblems, and their memorie ought to be filled with the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive places of Scripture.</note>§. 49. III. We muſt more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over reckon amongſt the means of exerciſing the minds of Young Ones with pleaſure, the preſenting them with Books of Spiritual Emblems, ſuch as theſe of <hi>Francis Querels.</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:179950:43"/>
And for the memorie, we cannot fill it with a more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Treaſure then with ſelec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted portions of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, particularly out of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the <hi>Parables,</hi> and dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>courſes of our Saviour, and ſome obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and remarkable parcels out of the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> and even out of the book of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> which though it be <hi>Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal,</hi> yet we would do well to make them not only often read it, but alſo to learn it by heart, as being full of Divine, and very excellent Moralitie.</p>
               <p n="50">§. 50. III. Young Ones are ſo naturally carried and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to <hi>Joy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>50.</hi> Young ones very inclinable to Joy. An account of the facultie of Rejoycing. The ground of it very early and deplor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably miſtaken.</note> that one may ſay, that it is as it were the deſign and end of thoſe little Creatures; And if we narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mark it, we ſhall find that even all other men do not propoſe to themſelves any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aim but this in all their enterprizes, and in all their travels, <hi>Joy</hi> or the facultie of Rejoycing, is, if we may ſo call it; the final and perfective facultie of our Souls, which in effect
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:179950:44"/>
were made for nothing elſe but to ſolace themſelves in joy, in pleaſure and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, without which it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to have any reſt or eaſe.</p>
               <p>But it is the misfortune and unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of men, that placing at firſt their Joy in that which is not ſolid, they do thereby commit from their very infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie an errour, which being continued ſhall make them infallibly loſe Eternal Joy and Bleſſedneſs.</p>
               <p n="51">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>51. 1.</hi> GOD only the true ground of rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and not our ſelves and any periſhable and worldly things. This Young Ones muſt timouſly be made ſenſible of.</note>§. 51. 1. It is moſt neceſſary to inculcat on Young Ones, as ſoon as ever it can be done, that ſince men are miſerable ſinners, ignorant, weak, and ſuch as ſhall rot in the earth, and ſince all that which is in the world, is likewiſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany, vain, and ſhall end by the fire, we muſt not place our Joy in any of thoſe things.</p>
               <p>We muſt not then rejoice in pleaſing men, or in being eſteemed or praiſed by them, in being well done to, well cloathed, well provided for, and well accommodat in all things; for all theſe things ſhall periſh for ever, and all the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:179950:44"/>
Joyes of this World ſhall terminat and end in a ſadneſs which ſhall be ſo much the more ſenſibly afflicting, as theſe Joyes have been more ſenſibly reliſhed, and as we have ſet our hearts more paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onatly on them.</p>
               <p>But ſince that <hi>GOD</hi> alone is Great, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Good, and the Author of all Good, we muſt not rejoice in any thing but in him only, in his only Will, and in doing of that only Wiſe, only Good, and only Eternal and Durable Will.</p>
               <p n="52">§. 52.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>52.</hi> Certain grounds of rejoice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be inculcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Young Ones.</note> We muſt therefore betimes excite Young Ones to rejoice in <hi>God,</hi> and in His Holy Will, For inſtance;</p>
               <p n="1">1. With reſpect to <hi>God,</hi> let them rejoice in this namely, that they have an Eternal and Almighty <hi>God</hi> to be their Father, who did make them with deſign to fill them with a Divine and Eternal Joy, if they will do his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Will, if they will love Him and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Him, and not love the honour, the goods, nor the pleaſures of this World, which ſhall laſt but a little time.</p>
               <p>Let them rejoice in this, that this GOD is without beginning and without end, incomprehenſible, and more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:179950:45"/>
then we are able to think; that he can do all things, that he doth all things, that he is only Wiſe to teach us well, and to govern us well, that he is Juſt, that he is Good, and a continuall Spring of all good things, that he is Faithfull in his promiſes of Eternal Life, that he is happy and glorious in himſelf.</p>
               <p>Let them rejoice moreover in this, that God only deſerves to be deſired, Known, Eſteemed, Loved, Praiſed, and Glorified for ever.</p>
               <p>Let them rejoice in this, that GOD hath aſſumed our Nature, that he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our Brother; and that he will take us for ever with himſelf unto his holy Fellowſhip in Heaven, and that even in this World he will come and dwell in our hearts, if we deſire him and do His Will.</p>
               <p>Let them praiſe him and thank him for His Goodneſs, as well as for the knowledge which they have of it, and the Joy which they have in it.</p>
               <p n="53">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>53. 2.</hi> They muſt be taught to rejeice when any thing is pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly done, whither by themſelve or by others, as alſo when they ſuffer &amp; are reproached and diſgraced.</note>§. 53. 2. By the ſame mean &amp; from the principles we ſhall make them eaſily underſtand that when any thing is done according to the <hi>Will of GOD,</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:179950:45"/>
whither by our ſelves or by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we ought to rejoice at it, as when our <hi>deſires,</hi> and our <hi>minds</hi> are formed and manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the manner I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>already declared, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it will be profitable to let them ſee an Application in particular inſtances. And that on the contrar, when any thing is done by Mans own will, and according to it, inſtead of rejoicing at it, we ſhould be ſad and grieved at it.</p>
               <p>For this reaſon it is that we ought to be ſenſibly afflicted for; and very deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bewail the ſins committed againſt God, whether by our ſelves or by others, ſince when we ſin, we follow our own wills in a diſregard and rejection of the Will of God.</p>
               <p>Further when Men do eſteem us, and when they praiſe us; if we were Wiſe, we would be troubled at it, and we would ſay to God, <q>LORD, who art only good, and the cauſe of all good, it is Thou alone who ought to be praiſed; and it is a ſhamefull robbery in the miſerable creature, to deſire to take to it ſelf that Eſteem, and that praiſe which do appertain but to Thee alone.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:179950:46"/>On the other hand, when we are deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed and undervalued, or when any doth us any injurie, or when we have not to our full content the things which we deſire, we ought to rejoyce at all theſe in our hearts, taking them as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo diſpenſed to us by the hand of our Heavenly Father, and be content with them, and ſay unto GOD<q>LORD, I deſerve nothing but reproaches, ſorrows and deſtitution, when I have theſe I have that which in juſtice belongeth to me, and therefore I rejoyce that thy Divine Juſtice is thus manifeſted in me. Even I give thee thanks, and I deſire no leſs to rejoice in this, that thy holy will is accompliſhed in me af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, for it is thy will that we ſhould be like to JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST; Now JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST hath been deſpiſed in this World, he hath been ill treated in it, rejected, callumniated, injuried, hated, and perſecuted, he had not his eaſe nor his pleaſure in it, but he lived in it in great want, in ſhame and in paine. Give me the grace and the ſtrength to follow him with Joy and courage, and by little and little as occaſion ſhall offer it ſelf, ſince that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo Reign with him. 1</hi>
                     <bibl> Tim. <hi>2.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="54">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:179950:46"/>[§. 54.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>54.</hi> The uſe of the facultie of Joy with reſpect to the particulars imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly preceeding illuſtrated by a compariſon.</note> This uſe of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of <hi>Rejocing</hi> may be very palpably made evident to Children by this ſimilitude; That as a ſick perſon does ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wiſely when he takes with joy an approved cure, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though very bitter, becauſe that being preſcribed by askilful and wiſe Phyſician, it certainly procures the health of the body; Juſt ſo do we ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wiſely, and as we ought, when we receive with joy all the treatments which GOD diſpenſes unto us, how bitter ſo ever they may appear; Becauſe they are ordered us by the moſt wiſe and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Phyſician of our Souls, which by the uſe of theſe excellent preſcripts do recover aſſuredly, not only their health, but a Life Eternally Happy; And as on the other hand a ſick perſon would act very fooliſhly, if he pleaſed himſelf in making uſe of whatever is agreeable to his guſt and reliſh, ſince by ſo doing he would not only increaſe his diſtemper, but alſo procure death; Even ſo it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable folly in ſinners, to make uſe of theſe things with joy, which pleaſe their corrupted will, and their ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:179950:47"/>
ſince at the cloſe and upſhot they can gather no other fruits of them, but their perdition and eternal death, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that word of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that the <hi>inclination</hi> and will, or <hi>guſt of the fleſh is the Death of the Soul.</hi> Rom. 8.6.]</p>
               <p n="55">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>55. III.</hi> Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent divertiſement muſt be allowed Young Ones, but with two cautions.</note>§. 55. III. But ſince it is impoſſible to ſuppreſs in Young Ones a thouſand and a thouſand acts of joy; which they bring forth at every turn on the account of natur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al things, which do agreeably flatter our ſenſes, and ſince it is even ſometimes neceſſary to allow them ſomething which may divert and recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate them, it will be profitable here to obſerve two things.</p>
               <p n="56">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>56. 1.</hi> That they muſt be made to acknowledge GOD to be the principal Author and Beſtower of whatever they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and to thank him for it.</note>§. 56. 1. One is, that when Young Ones do rejoyce whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the account of ſome gift which hath been beſtowed on them, and which regards their meat or their cloaths, or on the account of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing that is acceptable, unto them, we muſt be ſure to make them ſenſible, that all this is created by GOD,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:179950:47"/>
and that it comes from him, to the end that they may thank Him for it, that they may thank that GOD hath a thouſand and a thouſand times more and more excellent things to give ſuch as love him, and obey him, and are ready for the love of him to quite all theſe little things, when they ſhall know that it is his will ſo to do.</p>
               <p n="57">§. 57. 2. The other thing is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>57. 2.</hi> To be infinitly tonder of making theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or whtaever may gratifie their corrupt inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be the ground of their joy.</note> that we ought to be ware as we would be of death, to awaken the Joy of Young Ones, and the motions of pleaſure in their tender heart by objects of this nature, in promiſing and preſenting theſe unto them, in praiſing and valuing them, and in exciting them to take, reliſh, and rejoice in theſe things, ſo as people commonly do by means of ſweet meats and fine cloaths, of ſome pieces of Gold or Silver, or ſome pleaſing thing which we let them ſee, and even by a certain allowance which we give them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when they are faſhions, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſome ſtroaks of vengeance even on inanimat things, to the end that their anger or their hatred may flee over, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:179950:48"/>
that ſo they may become well pleaſed. In which people do that ſpiritually, for which God reproaches the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Pſalms, <hi>That they offered in Sacrifice th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> Sons and their Daughters to devils.</hi> Pſalm 106.</p>
               <p n="58">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>58. 3.</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the love of money is to be ſuppreſſed in them, of which they muſt be taught not to deſire more then ſerves their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and imploy what is over in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and charitable uſes.</note>§. 58. 3. We muſt in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, take ſpecial care to hinder the love of money from ſpringing up, and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Children; this is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the <hi>God</hi> of the World, the getting and poſſeſſion of which, all make the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal deſign and end they level at, and in which they make their happineſs, wellfare and joy to conſiſt: Which is an Idolatrie as damnable, and as pernicious as that of the Heathens. We muſt make them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that Money (which would be but of little or no value in the World if Charity did live in it, whereas no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is baniſhed from it) is but a low and poor mean to procure from the people of the World, ſomethings neceſſary to our life, that we muſt not deſire any more of it, then what ſerves our neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:179950:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
That GOD to whom it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, as all other things do, and to whom we muſt make an account of it, giving us leave to ſerve our ſelves of it for our neceſſity, wills that the reſt ſhould be for the poor and for his Glory. And in ſtead of accuſtoming to heap up little treaſures, we muſt Incline and prompt them, now and then, to give alms un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poor themſelves, out of any thing they have, as alſo to buy ſome uſeful thing, or ſome book of pietie for their inſtruction, and to rejoyce in this good uſe they make of what they have ſince it hath for its end the Glorie of God; Out of which it is not reaſonable that any ſhould rejoyce.</p>
               <p n="59">§. 59.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>59.</hi> GOD en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the Soul with the faculty of rejoycing, that it might be fixed on Himſelf.</note> The facultie of <hi>Joy</hi> and of pleaſure hath been made for GOD, <hi>Rejoice in the LORD evermore,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 4.4. And to that ſame purpoſe very often the Holy <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> particularly, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 37.4. <hi>Delight thy ſelf in the LORD, and He will give thee the deſire of thine heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="60">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:179950:49"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>60.</hi> The abuſe of our Joy, with reſpect to Divine and Spiritual Things to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and how</note>[§. 60. In fine, Since it is very poſſible for us to make an ill uſe of our Joy, in Divine and Spirituall Things, and ſince it is not meet to ſuffer the Seeds of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity to be ſown, and ſpring up in the Hearts of Young Ones from their tender years, let us endeavour to diſcover in a manner ſuited to their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, That is, by an eaſie and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Compariſon, how they ought to carry in this Affair.</p>
               <p>We muſt conſider GOD and His Grace, under the notion of a vaſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and remark how a Man would do with a Treaſure in different Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Rencounters.</p>
               <p>When one poſſeſſes an immenſe Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure fully, and without danger of loſing it any more, his Joy is then wholly pure and perfect. This it is, that the Joys of the Bleſſed are, ſince they poſſeſs GOD after this manner, that is without any fear or danger of ever loſing Him.</p>
               <p>But when one doth poſſeſs ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Treaſure but imperfectly, and that every moment he may loſe it, as well by the malice of an infinitie of moſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:179950:49"/>
cunning and perpetually reſtleſs enemies, as by his own Actions, by his negligence, and by his preſumption, it is evident that the Joy which one hath in theſe Circumſtances, ought to be tempered with a moſt ſerious Fear. This is it, which even the beſt muſt do during this Life, with reſpect to the Treaſure of Divine Grace. Hence St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorting the Saints of <hi>Philippi</hi> to <hi>rejoyce in the LORD,</hi> doth with the ſame breath enjoyn them, <hi>To work out their Salvation with fear and trembling,</hi> Phil: 2.12. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> having commended in thoſe who had a firm and ſteadie Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, That <hi>they rejoyced in Him with Joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> repreſents unto them, that ſince he whom <hi>they invock as their Father,</hi> ſhall alſo be their <hi>Judge,</hi> and will tender un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, even as to all others, <hi>according to their works, and without having reſpect to the difference of perſons,</hi> they ought therefore <hi>to live in fear, during the time that they ſojourn on earth,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.17. And the Holy Ghoſt ſayes on the ſame head, That, <hi>Bleſſed is he who feareth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes,</hi> Prov: 25.14.</p>
               <p>But if we, after having loſt this great Treaſure by our own fault, do ſee and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:179950:50"/>
poſſeſs nothing in its room, but pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and miſeries, but that nevertheleſs a promiſe ſhould be made to us of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it again reſtored, providing that we be ſenſibly touched with its loſs, and that afterwards we do manage our ſelves well in every thing that ſhall be intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us, there is then indeed very good Reaſon <hi>to rejoyce in this Hope,</hi> though in the mean time we ought not to be leſs afflicted with the fault, and with the loſs of the time paſt, and with the preſent miſerie and deſolation: Neither ought we to be without a Holy Fear, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the time to come, from the conſideration of our own weakneſs and skilleſſleſs to govern our ſelves well; This is it, that we muſt ſtill do with reſpect to GOD and His Divine Graces. <hi>David</hi> ſayes, that when he thought on his ſins and that he had loſt his GOD, he did nothing but lament and weep both day and night, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 6.32.38.42. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And GOD proteſts that He will not communicate himſelf to any, but to thoſe who ſhall have an <hi>Afflicted Heart</hi> for having loſt him, a <hi>contrite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> for having offended Him, and who <hi>tremble at His Words,</hi> fearing leaſt they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:179950:50"/>
ſhould not continue faithful to them. <hi>To this man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will I look, even to him that is poor, and of a contrite Spirit, and trembleth at my Word,</hi> Iſa: 66.2. And Jeſus Chriſt ſaith very expreſly that Conſolation ſhall be given to thoſe that Weep, (namely for their own ſins, and for the ſins of others) and he pronounces them <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> Math: 5.5.</p>
               <p>But when without theſe wholeſome Precautions we would have nothing but feelings of Joy and Gladneſs, this Joy becomes then eaſily the Neſt of Self-love, the ground of Self-ſatisfaction, and the intertainment of a Blindneſs, which hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from us the greatneſs of our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hinders us from making enquirie after its cure, and which, makes us car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally preſume, that we poſſeſs the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Riches, becauſe that we perſwade our ſelves that we have them, though not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we are far removed from them, as may be ſeen in the Church of <hi>Loadicea,</hi> who being wholly content, with it ſelf, and with its own ſtate, did ſay ſo preſumptuouſly, <hi>I am rich and increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in goods, and have lake of nothing;</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, alas! Jeſus Chriſt in the mean time replyes to her, <hi>But thou knoweſt not that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:179950:51"/>
thou art wretched, miſerable, poor, naked, and blind,</hi> Rev: 3.17. And in his Goſpel, <hi>Luke.</hi> 6.24. Denounces <hi>Woe,</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, mourning,</hi> and <hi>tears</hi> againſt the <hi>Rich</hi> and the full (that is, who fancy themſelves to be ſuch without any juſt ground) and againſt thoſe <hi>inconſiderate wretches,</hi> whom St. <hi>James</hi> calls upon <hi>to feel their miſeries, to weep and to lament, to change their Laughter into tears, and their Joyes into ſadneſs,</hi> James 4.9 Without which the Wiſe Man ſayes, That <hi>the hard and inſenſible heart ſhall fall into miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief,</hi> Prov: 28.14.</p>
               <p>And therefore it is an Effect of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom, to know well how to temper our Joy with fear, and our ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with Joy. <hi>The Fear of the LORD is the beginning of Wiſdom,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> and elſewhere, <hi>Happy is the man that fears the LORD, and that delighteth greatly in His Commandments,</hi> Pſal: 111. and 112. The ſame Prophet adviſes thoſe, who would have either the Grace or the Glory of Jeſus Chriſt exhibited unto them, to ſet about it with a ſubmiſſion mingled with Fear and with Joy, <hi>Serve the LORD with Fear and rejoyce with Trembling,</hi> Pſal: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.11. Whereas the falſe Prophets do
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:179950:51"/>
nothing elſe but ſpeak indiſtinctly and ſolely of Joy, Peace and Aſſurance, <hi>Ezek:</hi> 13.16, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5.3.</p>
               <p n="16">§. 16. IV.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>61. IV.</hi> the Divine Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul, are well ordered, action eaſily and naturallie follows, but it muſt not be ſuſpended till that be done ſince outward exerciſes have a good influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the inward man.</note> When the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Joy,</hi> and <hi>Deſire</hi> are ſet Right, and well faſhioned, all the reſt follows of its own accord. But ſince it is neceſſary that we be active and doing, even before that the inward man be yet well diſpoſed, and that moreover the inward man is ordinarly aided by the Outward, it is needful to have at hand ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Rules for <hi>Action,</hi> and for the Conduct and Mannagement of the Outward Converſation.</p>
               <p n="62">§. 62. <hi>Our bodies and our life belonging of Right to GOD,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>62.</hi> The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rule of action laid down, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and illuſtrated by ſome particular inſtances.</note> 
                  <hi>we muſt diſpoſe of them, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our own will, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[Since <hi>our will</hi> is naturalie turned towards our ſelves, towards our <hi>advantages,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our <hi>Honour,</hi> and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and therefore doth
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:179950:52"/>
beget in us the mortal vices of <hi>avarice, Pride,</hi> and <hi>ſenſuality,</hi> (which obſtruct in us the operations of GOD, and Rob us of the Salvation of our Souls) we muſt in order to root them up, practiſe ſelf-denyal in every thing, and we muſt be at pains to accuſtom Children betimes, and as much as poſſibly we can, with the Divine aid; to do every thing by a Spirit of <hi>Charity,</hi> and for the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by a Spirit of <hi>Humility,</hi> without deſign or deſire that men ſhould eſteem or Honour us, and by a Spirit of <hi>Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> without regarding our own ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction whither of Soul or of Body, but aſpiring after a conformitie to the <hi>Crucified JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and dying in our own account on the Croſs without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
               <p>This is the true Spirit of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Life and <hi>practice,</hi> and of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, a Spirit wholly oppoſite to that of corrupted nature, by which alas! Men ſuffer themſelves to be drawn ſweetly, and as it were laughing unto Eternal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, without ever thinking on it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The will of GOD is,</hi> that we ſhould do nothing but in order to pleaſe him, His pleaſure is to be glorified by our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:179950:52"/>
His Glory ought to be our Soveraign, abſolute &amp; Univerſal end, and we ought to look on our Salvation as a mean to advance this end of Bleſſing Praiſing and Glorifying for ever his Divine Majeſtie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Glory of GOD</hi> is advanced in this life when we give place in our hearts to the force and vertue of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and when we ſuffer his Power and his Ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie to beget by us a great many Holy actions, for which we have Juſt ground to Honour, Bleſs and Praiſe the Divine cauſe, (that is, the Power and the Efficacie of GOD) whence ſuch excellent things do iſſue, &amp; which contains in it ſelf infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly more of them. <hi>He who abides in me,</hi> ſaith JESUS CHRIST, <hi>and in whom I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, brings forth much Fruit, for without me ye can do nothing. And herein is my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Glorified, that ye bring forth much fruit, Jo.</hi> 15.5, 8. And elſewhere, <hi>Let men ſee your good works, that they may Glorifie your Father which is in Heaven.</hi> Matt. 5 16.</p>
               <p>This may and ought to be extended to all ſorts of <hi>actions</hi> and things, becauſe whatever we do, ought to be done for the Glory of GOD, and becauſe nothing can be well done but in the <hi>Name,</hi> that is, by the Power, by the Bleſſing, and by
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:179950:53"/>
the Direction of JESUS CHRIST. <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye eat or drink, or whatſoever ye do, do all to the Glorie of GOD.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. And <hi>whatſover ye do, in word or in deed, do all in the Name of our LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST. Col.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <p>Thus, for inſtance, we eat and drink for the Glorie of GOD, &amp; in the Name of JESUS CHRIST, when we do it from a Principle, and in a way com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and taught us by him, and which prompts us to ſay from our very "heart <q>
                     <hi>Suffer me not, O LORD! To eat and drink only as do the Beaſts, by a meer brutal appetite, and for a life only natural; And much leſs, in following the diſorders of our corrupted natures: But grant that by the Power, and by the direction of the Holy Spirit of Thy Son JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, I may eat and drink according to thine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, ſo much as is neceſſary for the maintaining of a life which I will imploy in loving thee, in bleſſing thee, and in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee, in following by thy grace the life of our Redeemer.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Juſt ſo we ſpeak to the Glory of GOD, and in the Name of JESUS CHRIST, when we ſeek from him, and receive from him, the force and grace, to ſay
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:179950:53"/>
nothing but what is regulated by him, but what is neceſſary, and what is prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſuggeſt good thoughts to men, and to turn them from evil and vain things.</p>
               <p>In a word, we do all in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, and to the Glory of GOD, when having ſought before all things, the Divine Grace and Vertue of Jeſus Chriſt, we do by it, and according to the Will of GOD, from a Divine Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and to a Divine End, whatſoever we have to do, following that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable leſſon of St. <hi>Peter. Let every one of you according as he hath received the Grace &amp; Gift of GOD, make uſe of it for the Good of others, as being faithful diſpenſers of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Grace of GOD. If any man ſpeak, let him do it as delivering words flowing from the Virtue of GOD, if any one doth ſervice to others, let him do it as acting by the Power which GOD gives: To the end that in every thing we do, God may be glorified by Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Praiſe, and Dominion for ever and ever.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.10.11.]</p>
               <p n="63">§. 63. <hi>The Will of GOD</hi> is marked in his <hi>Commandments,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>63.</hi> The Will of GOD, which is the Rule of our Obedience, is made known to us on his Precepts, which muſt be taught Young Ones firſt in the literal &amp; then in the more Sublime and Spiritual Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of them.</note> which we muſt cauſe Young Ones learn, and which we muſt explain unto them at
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:179950:54"/>
firſt according to the Letters and as their Capacities will allow; And afterwards, when they are capable of it, we muſt make them underſtand, that the Law being <hi>Spiritual, God</hi> by his Commands, enjoyns us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That we love nothing but Himſelf alone, and for His ſake only.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That we do not think that GOD is like to the thoughts and the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, that our dark reaſon and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment make us apprehend of him: Nor that the way of ſerving and pleaſing of him, is the work of our own will, and of our own fancie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That we do not make uſe of <hi>his Name,</hi> of his Covenant, of his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of his Grace, of being the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of GOD, <hi>in vain,</hi> and without profiting by them, and bringing foth Fruits agreeable to them, and that we take head that we do not cloak our ſelf will our paſſions, our deſigns, our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ways, and even our wickedneſs and crimes under the ſacred prete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts of the <hi>Name of GOD,</hi> of His Truth, of His Juſtice, of His Glory, and of his Intereſt.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:179950:54"/>4. That we muſt <hi>ceaſe labouring,</hi> acting and living by our own will, to the End that GOD may Labour, and Work, and Live in us and by us.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That we ought to <hi>Honour</hi> the Word, the Will, and the good Inſpirations of GOD, by which He would beget us Spiritually and make us new Creatures, who may live long on the Land which He ſhall give us, that is, enjoy Life E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That we ought not to <hi>Kill</hi> in us the Image of GOD, take away the ſpiritual Life from our Souls by our ſins, nor kill the Soul of our neighbours by the examples of an Heatheniſh, worldly and wicked life.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That we ought not to ſerve our ſelves of any creature for meer pleaſure without neceſſity, and without having allowance from the will of GOD: This is that which conſtitutes the <hi>Whooredom</hi> of of the heart. <hi>Jam:</hi> 4.3, 4.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That we ought not to ſteal from GOD (to whom every thing doth appertain) either our affections, or our life, or our time, or goods, or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in imploying them any other way then for him.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb facs="tcp:179950:55"/>9. That of our ſelves, and without the Light of GOD we ought not to <hi>Judge</hi> of any perſon: For otherwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as we are in darkneſs, we will Judge falſly, and ſin grivouſly againſt GOD.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That being content with what we have, we ought not to deſire any more; for every deſire of having more is that <hi>covetouſneſs</hi> which is forbidden.</p>
               <p n="64">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>64.</hi> Though what the Law commands be impoſſible to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted nature, yet the Spirit of Jeſus makes in an eaſie yoke.</note>§. 64. And in fine, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that which the Law requires, be impoſſible to the fleſh, becauſe of ſin, which hath weakened it, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs when GOD gives the Good Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt to a Soul, it doth then by his aſſiſtance, or rather the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt doth then in that ſoul, all that the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; Without doing which, none can as yet pretend to the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, neither doth any as yet belong to him as his Child, nor as juſtified by him. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.3, 4, 9. Nor as having true faith, which doth not make void the Law, but eſtabliſh it, <hi>Rom:</hi> 3.30. By which alſo we keep the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of GOD in overcoming the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:179950:55"/>
World. <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.3, 4. And which in fine, admits us into a communion with GOD in the Light, and into a ſtate, out of which we cannot partake in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Jeſus Chriſt, and of his Death: Since, <hi>If we ſay than we haue fellowſhip with GOD, and yet walk in darkneſs we lie, and do not the truth: But if we walk in the Light, as he is in the Light, we have fellowſhip one with another, and then the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt His Son cleanſes us from all ſin,</hi> ſaith St. John. 1 John. 1.6, 7.</p>
               <p n="65">§. 65. The <hi>Will</hi> of GOD, as to that we muſt practiſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>65.</hi> Portions of Scripture particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larized, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Goſpel Law, the peruſal whereof muſt be ſpecially recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to young ones.</note> is alſo ſet down very particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie, and in brief in the 5, 6, and 7 Chap: of St. <hi>Mat:</hi> And in the 13, 14, 15, and 16 of St. <hi>John,</hi> and in the firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>John,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter.</hi> All which muſt be made very familiar to young ones, together with the great Pſalm of <hi>David,</hi> by the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Section, whereof, we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſhut up the reading of the menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned portions of Holy <hi>Scripture.</hi> To theſe we may alſo joyn <hi>Thomas</hi> a <hi>Kempis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="66">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:179950:56"/>[§. 66. All the Laws of GOD which are ſo whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>66.</hi> An Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſhort ſumm of the Divine Laws, which muſt be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefully im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>printed on the hearts of Young Ones.</note> and ſo admirable, whereof <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks ſo oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with ſo much love and admiration, which all the Scripture recommends as the ſource of life, as the light of the heart, as the Treaſure of Souls, which Jeſus Chriſt calls Eternal Life <hi>Joh:</hi> 12.50. And which, in fine, the Holy Spirit promiſed, Writes in the heart where he dwels, ſay all the Laws of GOD may be reduced to theſe four.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To Love GOD.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To Love Jeſus Chriſt Crucified, (that is, not only himſelf, but alſo his Croſs and his Tribulations, the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his Afflictions, conformity to his Death, and the fulfilling of what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind of his Sufferings in our fleſh. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.2. <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.10. <hi>Col:</hi> 1.24.)</p>
               <p n="3">3. To love our neighbour.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And to hate our ſelves.</p>
               <p>The whole of our duty is truely comprehended under theſe few heads; Therefore it is that we muſt take pains to inſpire the Veneration, and love of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:179950:56"/>
them into the hearts of <hi>Children,</hi> &amp; ſo to ſay into the Marrow of their bones from their tender years, and to animate them thereto by Prayer, by meditation, and by the dayly reading of that incompare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> which hath been already mentioned; as alſo by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of thoſe excellent words of his in the 19 Pſalm; <hi>The Law of the Lord</hi> (the Law of the love of God, &amp; of the Croſs of Jeſus Chriſt, the love of our Neighbour, and the hatred of ſelf:) This admirable Law when it is imprinted on the Heart by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Is a Law that is intire &amp; perfect, &amp; converts the Soul. The Teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, and makes the ſimple, even little Children wiſe. The Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are right, rejoycing the Heart. The Statutes of the Lord are pure, and they enlighten the eyes of our ſoul. The fear of the Lord is the ſource of Holineſs, it is the only good that ſhall endure for ever. The Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the LORD are true and Righteous altogether, more are they to be deſired than Gold, yea then much fine Gold, ſweeter alſo then Hony, and the Hony-comb, By them is thy ſervant enlightened, and in keeping of them is a great reward.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="67">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:179950:57"/>[§. 67. It will be alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profitable,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>67.</hi> Children muſt be put in mind of the Baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Covenant, as alſo of the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages and duties of it.</note> and even ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to repreſent unto Children, that at their Baptiſm they entered into a Covenant with GOD, who on His part hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be their GOD, that is to ſay, to give himſelf, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt unto them, with all his good things, and with all his graces, whereof then they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the firſt fruits, which they ſhould take care not to looſe by their ſins; and by an Antichriſtian converſation, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering that they alſo on their part have reciprocally promiſed unto GOD to be entirely his, and to give and conſecrate unto him for ever their Souls and their bodies, their deſires, &amp; their underſtandings, their pleaſures, and their Joyes, their actions, and their whole life, together with a filial obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all the expreſſions of his moſt Holy will, and an abſolute and full renounciation of ſelf, and ſin of the Devil and the World, thus ratifieing in ſubſtance all thoſe things which we have hitherto inſiſted on, and which none
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:179950:57"/>
can neglect without renouncing his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and Chriſtianitie.]</p>
               <p n="68">§. 68. I ſuppoſe that all the World knows well enough the moſt common rules concerning what Young Ones ought to practiſe with reſpect to God,<note place="margin">68. What Young Ones muſt practiſe</note> their Parents, their Neighbours &amp; them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, things which ought to be inculcat very carefully on them, by reaſon that ſuch is the Will of God; As,</p>
               <p n="69">§. 69. 1. With regard to God.<note place="margin">69. 1. With reſpect to God.</note>
               </p>
               <p>[To live and to act as being alwayes in the preſence of God, who together with all his Holy Angels, ſtill looks on us, and who will make to come into his Judgement whatſoever we have done, ſpoke or thought, whether Good or evil, in order to be rewarded or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for it for ever.]</p>
               <p>To pray unto God orderly Evening and Morning, and before Meals.</p>
               <p>To make them often lift up their heart to God, particularly before any labour or imployment in order to obtain his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and Bleſſing; and after they have finiſhed their work, to return Thanks to God for it; and offer it up to Him, and to His Glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:179950:58"/>To hear with reſpect and Attention the Divine Truths, whether in private, or at Church, without thinking that they have ſufficiently diſcharged their Duty to God, for having ſimply heard them, or retained them in their Memories, and that therefore they ought to pray unto God that he would give the true Underſtanding of them, and by the Operations of his Good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit quicken them, ſo as to bring forth Fruit in an Humble, ſubmiſſive, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and ſimple heart.</p>
               <p n="70">
                  <note place="margin">70. 2. With reſpect to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents &amp; Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors.</note>§. 70, 2. With reſpect to Fathers and Mothers, and Superiours.</p>
               <p>To pray unto God for them.</p>
               <p>To love them with fear and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
               <p>To obey them without murmuring, even in thoſe things which do not pleaſe us, and which are not evidently ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his Commandments.</p>
               <p>And to do nothing without their Knowledge and allowance.</p>
               <p n="71">
                  <note place="margin">71 1. With reſpect to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</note>§. 71. 3. With regard to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and Play-fellows.</p>
               <p>To pray alſo unto GOD for them;</p>
               <p>To love them, and to wiſh Good to them as to themſelves, and not to do
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:179950:58"/>
unto them but as they would that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould do unto them.</p>
               <p>To believe them to be better then themſelves, and not to prefer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to any.</p>
               <p>To live in peace with them, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear them, and never to revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, either by deſire or by injuries, or any other way, of the evil which they may have met with from them; but heartily to pardon them,<note place="margin">72 4. with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</note> and even to pray unto GOD very particularly for them.</p>
               <p n="72">§. 72. 4. With regard to themſelves,</p>
               <p>To have alwayes a very mean opinion of themſelves.</p>
               <p>To eat only at appointed hours ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and of whatſoever is given them, whither it be agreeable or diſagreeable to them.</p>
               <p>Not to deſire either Pomp, or Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to be content with little.</p>
               <p>To imploy their time according to the Rules preſcribed them, never being without ſome work, idleneſs being the devils pillow.</p>
               <p>To do whatever is recommended to them the beſt way they can.</p>
               <p>Not to lie, nor diſput, nor contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:179950:59"/>
nor ſpeak unprofitably, not to ſeek for excuſes when they have failed, but to be ready to confeſs ingenuouſly their faults, and to beg pardon from GOD, from their Superiours, and from their neighbours, to the end they may obtain the favour of God, who will never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſins as long as they are excuſed.</p>
               <p n="73">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>73.</hi> How to mannage the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes and Chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſo as they may tend to their Benefit and Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>[§. 73. Touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs and chaſtiſements of Children, I ſuppoſe that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and others concerned are not ignorant that with reſpect to ſuch as are of a Docile, Peaceable, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Temper, they muſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence more of Lenity and Sweetneſs than of Severitie; And that on the contrary, they ought to teſtifie more of ſeverity to thoſe that are of a Fierce, Obſtinate, and mutinous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſetting them however underſtand, that it is only their wicked qualities, and Diſpoſitions which hinder, that they are not ſo much loved, as otherwiſe they would be.</p>
               <p>It is Equitable and Juſt to pardon Children faults which they have done, without deſign by ignorance and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:179950:59"/>
thinking to do evil; though in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mean time, they ſhould take occaſion from theſe miſcarriages, thus ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and undeſignedly committed, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in, and to exhort them to their Duty: But great care muſt be taken to puniſh ſuch faults as they commit wilfully, and knowing well that they do evil; as the faults of lying, of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of ſtricking ſome bodie, and the like.</p>
               <p>We muſt never chaſtiſe Children without letting them underſtand before hand, as much as may be that they are to be blamed, that they have done that which they knew ought not to be done, and that it is Juſt that they ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for it, for their Good, and by the Love which we carrie to them.</p>
               <p>Theſe Principles are well enough ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their Capacitie, namely. that evil diſpleaſes GOD &amp; Men, that it deſerves puniſhment before GOD &amp; before Men, that if it were not puniſhed, it would grow, and could not be curbed any more, and it would be attended with Eternal Chaſtiſements: That in order to hinder this miſery, and to reſcue them from it by the Love which we bear to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:179950:60"/>
their Souls, it is good to let them a little taſte a chaſtiſement, which is a hundred thouſand Millions of times leſs then that of the other Life: And having thus repreſented theſe things unto them, to chaſtiſe them moderatly, without fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make them weep, and to renew the Chaſtiſement, when they reiterat the Crime, Reaſonable Chaſtiſements are the effect of True Love, and two or three of theſe given to a Child, who begins to contract ill habits, are capable to craze them; Whereas if we ſpare them by a fooliſh and fond love, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed rather a cruel hatred, we ſhall weep with them for it Eternally.</p>
               <p>But on the other hand, we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Brutiſh, Paſſionat, and indiſcreet Chaſtiſements, which are no leſs hurtful then too much Indulgence, and which have no other effect but to render their Spirits froward and untractable, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire them with horrour, as well at the good to which we would conſtrain them ſo cruelly, as at the perſons, which they cannot hinder themſelves from looking on as their enemies</p>
               <p n="74">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>74.</hi> Children muſt be taught to praiſe GOD, when they do well, and not to take the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of it to themſelves.</note>§. 74. When Children do well, and we give evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:179950:60"/>
of our being well ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſed thereat, it were far better to teach them to praiſe GOD for it, and to ſay to Him, <q>I thank Thee, O LORD, for vouchſafing me the grace to do well, without Thee I cannot do any thing that is worth;</q> then to praiſe themſelves directly for it, and that becauſe of the danger there is by ſo doing, of inſpiring them with, and fortifying in them, ſelf-love, ſelf ſatisfaction, and pride.]</p>
               <p n="75">ſſ. 75. There are yet many other things both to be prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed towards them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>75.</hi> Parents ought conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to practiſe themſelves what they recommend to their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> and to be taught them, which they who lay to heart as they ought their Education, may well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and inculcate on them of themſelves, or which they may deduce from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples hitherto laid down, which Fathers and Mothers ought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves firſt of all to practiſe, as well for their own Salvation, as for the Salvation of their Children, which ought to be as dear to them as their own, and this conſideration ſhould incline them to ſeek
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:179950:61"/>
from GOD without ceaſing, the Grace how to mannage and govern becoming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both themſelves and theſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them, and not to deſtroy by their Actions and by their examples, that which they do no otherways re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to their Children then by words baffled and diſcredited by their own practices.</p>
               <p n="76">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>76. 45.</hi> The ſuppoſed impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or ridiculouſneſs of the foregoing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections refuted, &amp; the miſerie of theſe Parents, who ſhall neglect them brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared.</note>§. 76. Perhaps theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts ſhall ſeem to the moſt part either impoſible, or ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous to be inculcated on and practiſed by Children. They do not appear to us impoſſible on any other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but becauſe we have not been from our infancie trained up to them; if there had been no defect here, theſe Precepts would appear unto us eaſineſs it ſelf. As for the imagined ridiculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them, if there be any ſuch thing in them, it is in that ſame ſenſe, that the Croſs of Jeſus Chriſt is fooliſhneſs, with reſpect to the Maxims of this world which is the enemie of GOD, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom whereof is fooliſhneſs before GOD; and of which the Scripture ſayes, <hi>Ye
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:179950:61"/>
Adulterers and Adultereſſes know ye not that the friendſhip of the World is emnity with GOD? Whoſoever therefore will be a friend of the World, is the enemie of GOD. Jam:</hi> 4.4. And pray conſider of what nature the Precepts are, which this Divine Word gives us on this head; <hi>Be not conformed to this world.</hi> Rom: 12.2. <hi>Love not the world nor the things of the World, if any man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him, For all that which is in the World, the Luſt of the eyes, the Luſt of the fleſh, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the World; And the World paſſeth away, and the luſt thereof, but he that doth the will of GOD abideth for ever.</hi> 1 Joh. 2.15, 16, 17. How unhappy then are they who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat their Children according to the Rules of the world, and for the world, that they may be mighty, Rich, well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodate, and eſteemed in the World, and that ſo they may in end periſh with the enemies of GOD, and with the World: Theſe Parents who thus train up their Children ſhall be accurſed by them through all Eternity in Hell, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have brought them, and which ſhall be common to them with their Children, for having done as theſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:179950:62"/>
miſerable <hi>Iſraelits</hi> did of Old, who ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed their Sons &amp; their Daughters to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; ſhed innocent blood, even the blood of their ſons &amp; of their daughters, whom they Sacrificed to the Idols of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="77">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>77.</hi> The great happyneſs of ſuch as ſhall train up their Children, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note>§. 77. But thrice happy are they, who deſpiſing the conduct and meaſures of the Antichriſtian, and Diabolical World, ſhall make it their dayly care to educate and dreſs the precious Souls of their Children for Eternity, according to the meaſures of the Holy Goſpel, and Rules of the Croſs of JESUS CHRIST: Such Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſhall certainly be Bleſſed Eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by their Children in Heaven, and all together ſhall Bleſs the LORD for ever, who alſo ſhall Bleſs them all, World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſalm <hi>103.15, 16, 17, 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>As for Man his dayes are as Graſs as a Flower of the field, ſo he flouriſheth: For the wind paſſeth over it, and it is gone and the place thereof ſhall know it no more. But the mercie of the Lord is from everlaſting to everlaſting u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them that fear him, and his Righteouſneſs unto Childrens Children to ſuch as keep his Covenants; And to thoſe that remember his commandments to do them.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:179950:62"/>
            <head>THE <hi>PRAYER OF</hi> RUSBROCHIUS, Tranſlated from the LATIN.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> My GOD! O Soveraign Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I beſeech Thee by Thy Infinite Mercy, to vouchſafe me the Grace to Love Thee with all my Heart, and above all things, and alſo to love all Men of whatſoever State &amp; Condition, whither Friends or Enemys as my ſelf. Give me a charitable and reſpectful Eſteem for them, and do not ſuffer me ever to judge nor to deſpiſe any Perſon, but that rather I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:179950:63"/>
to be deſpiſed and rejected my ſelf by all the World.</p>
            <p>Grant that I may never ſtudie to pleaſe Men, but to pleaſe Thee only; That I may not fear to diſpleaſe them, but to diſpleaſe Thee: And O let it be my chief and only Deſire, to promove alwayes Thy Honour, and to fulfil in all things Thy moſt agreeable Will.</p>
            <p>O moſt Amiable, and moſt Merciful Saviour, hinder me from truſting to my ſelf, and from leaning to my own acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to my own conduct: And grant that I may not truſt in any thing but in Thee alone, and in Thy moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Merits; So as, that placing all my Hope, and all my Confidence in theſe, I may notwithſtanding never neglect to do that which Thy Grace hath enabled me to do.</p>
            <p>Wound, O wound my Heart with the Darts of Thy Love, and deliver me from all the inclinations of impure and deceitful Self-love: Enlighten my eyes, and touch my Soul, in Order to give
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:179950:63"/>
me the true Knowledge and Senſe of Thy Love, of Thy Mercy, of Thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and of Thy Power; As alſo of my own nothingneſs, of my unbelief, of my darkneſs, of my folly, of my wickedneſs, of my miſerie, and of my weakneſs.</p>
            <p>O deareſt Redeemer, do not ſuffer me ever to loſe the memorie of Thy Death and Paſſion; But that I may make my recourſe to it, as unto an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured Refuge, and a Bleſsed Mean of approaching Thy Divine Majeſty; And that I may look on Thy Wounds as a Furnace of Love, where I may plunge and conſume all the powers of my Life, and of my Soul.</p>
            <p>O Prince of Love, fill me ſo with Thy Love, that for the ſake of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love, I may be alwayes ready to do, and to forſake all things: That for the ſake of Thy Love, all toil, and travel may be ſweet and eaſie unto me, that in fine, for the ſake of this Holy Love, all the Creatures, all their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, all their Joyes, and all their
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:179950:64"/>
Recreations, may become as bitter and as diſagreeable to me, as they have been hitherto pleaſing and acceptable; And that hereafter I may as chearfully ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the want of them, as I do yet feel a natural reluctancy to deprive my ſelf of them. Extinguiſh alſo, O my GOD, in the Hearts of all Men, the Thoughts and Natural Inclinations which they may have for me, and root out of my Heart the images both of them, and of all other outward things.</p>
            <p>Do not turn away from me, O Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, any of theſe afflictions, croſſes and ſufferings, which Thou pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es I ſhould endure, and which Thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall judge fit and uſeful to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance me towards Thee; But grant me the Grace, that by every tribulation &amp; by every adverſity which may befal me, whither directly from Thy Hand, or from Men as Thy Inſtruments, I may learn to acknowledge and confeſs my ſelf guiltie, and that I may deſpiſe and condemn my ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:179950:64"/>But eſpecially, O my dear Redeemer, I intreat that by the Merits of Thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Wounds, and of Thy Death, by Thy Self, and by all that is in Thee, it may pleaſe Thee to ſatisfie Thy Divine Father, for all the ſins which I have ever committed, and to ſupplie all my paſt negligences and defects. And for the time to come, grant me the Grace to have alwayes before my eyes, and with a Holy Fear, the hour of my Death, which is ſo uncertain; The rigour of Thy Judgement, which is ſo terrible; The ſhortneſs of my Life, whereof alas I have already ſo unprofitably, and for triffles, loſt the far better part; And the infinite and Eternal Puniſhments, which ſhall be inflicted on the wicked and ſinners.</p>
            <p>And grant in fine, O Infinite Bountie, that I may never, either ſeek, or find peace or pleaſure in any thing, but in Thy Self; And that Thou only may be Eternallie the Cauſe, and the Reaſon, and the Rule of my Conduct, and of all my Actions, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:65"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179950:65"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
